<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The minority of St. Lewis With the politick conduct of affairs by his mother Queen Blanch of Spain, during her regency. Being a relation of what happen'd most memorable under his reign during the year, 1226, 1227, 1228, and 1229.</title>
            <author>Philipps, Edward, 1630-1696?.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2130:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The minority of St. Lewis With the politick conduct of affairs by his mother Queen Blanch of Spain, during her regency. Being a relation of what happen'd most memorable under his reign during the year, 1226, 1227, 1228, and 1229.</title>
                  <author>Philipps, Edward, 1630-1696?.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 146, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Bentley and S. Magnes, at the Post-house in Russel-Street in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The dedication is signed: Edw. Philips.</note>
                  <note>The first "2" in "1227" is printed upside down on title page.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  IX, --  King of France, 1214-1270 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Blanche, --  of Castile, Queen, consort of Louis VIII, King of France, 1188-1252 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  History --  Arab period, 711-1492 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MINORITY OF St. Lewis.</p>
            <p>With the Politick Conduct of Affairs by his Mother Queen <hi>Blanch</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Regency.</p>
            <p>BEING A Relation of what happen'd moſt Memorable under his Reign du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Year, 1226, 1227, 1228, and 1229.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> at the Poſt-houſe in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Illuſtrous Prince, HENRY DUKE of <hi>NORFOLK,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> Earl of <hi>Arundel, Surrey, Norfolk,</hi> and <hi>Norwich,</hi> Baron <hi>Mowbray, Howard, Seagrave, Bruſe de Gower, Fitz-Allan, Clun, Oſwaldeſtrey, Maltravers, Talbot, Verdon, Lovetot, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nival, Strange, of Blackmere,</hi> and <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Caſtle Ryſing,</hi> Conſtable and Governour of His Majeſties Royal Caſtle and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Windſor,</hi> Lord Warden of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor Forreſt,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the Counties of <hi>Norfolk, Surrey</hi> and <hi>Berks,</hi> and of the City of <hi>Norwich</hi> and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſaid City, and Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Should not have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to approach with an Addreſs of ſo ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:36383:3"/>importance, a <hi>Perſonage</hi> of your Dignity and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, in whoſe preſent ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the Honours, and in whoſe Perſon all the Virtues of your Illuſtrious Family ſo eminently ſhine, but for this conſideration, that there is an obliging condiſcention which ever attends upon true Nobility and Native Greatneſs: But, my Lord, I have this moreover to plead, that in this ſo ſmall a Volume there, are ſuch <hi>Arcana Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriae,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:36383:3"/>and ſuch well weigh'd Characters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that thoſe even of the higheſt Sphaere and Imployment may, I judge, think a few hours not ill beſtow'd in the peruſal of them. The laſt pretenſion I lay to your Graces par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, is, that I have taken care to give your Grace as little interruption as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to your more weighty affairs, in ſtriving to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ambition I have of paying my Mite of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:36383:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>honours and reſpects which you merit from all the world, and thereby of aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Title of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>MY LORD, Your GRACES moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt dutiful Servant.</hi> Edw. Philips.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36383:4"/>
            <head>The MINORITY OF St. Lewis. OR, A Relation of what happen'd of moſt Memorable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Reign, during the Years, 1226, 1227, 1228, and 1229.</head>
            <p>NEver any Chriſtian Prince merited of Hiſtory more ſolid, ſerious, and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Praiſe than <hi>Lewis</hi> the 9th
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36383:5"/>of that Name, King of <hi>France,</hi> fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the Saint; and conſequently never any Chriſtian Prince hath been ſo ill treated by the generality of Hiſtorians, both <hi>French</hi> and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, Ancient and Modern, Good and Bad, of all ſorts of People, and of all Religions. The Hereticks of latter times haply offended at the Reaſon he gave for refuſing to go to ſee the Body of Chriſt become viſible in the hands of a Prieſt, namely, that he had no need of ocular Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to convince him of a Truth, whereof he was already ſo well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, have with that prejudice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented even the moſt Heroick of his actions, that, were their Credit valuable, this Prince could certainly be allow'd no better a Character than any of the nine laſt Kings of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovingian</hi> Race; They will needs have that haughtineſs wherewith he treated his Brother <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou,</hi> who after he was crown'd King
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36383:5"/>of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> let looſe the Reins to licence, paſs for an Effect of ſecret Pride and Ambition; they brand with raſhneſs and imprudence the two Expeditions he made againſt the Infidels, and will have the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Charge he was at in thoſe Undertakings, no other than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs and Prodigality. That Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Air which he expreſt in all his Actions, and which deſcended to him from the Queen his Mother, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret to be only a natural Surli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Auſterity of humour in him: and though more Covertly, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear not to cenſure his frequent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations, and regulations of Hoſpitals The plainneſs of his habit they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to a poorneſs of Spirit in him, and from his aptneſs to conceal and paſs over all private Injuries offer'd him, they are ready to accuſe him of Puſillanimity and Cowardice. His Converſation though obliging e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, they account too Reſerv'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36383:6"/>and Moroſe, conſidering the Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity and Freedom that had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to Courtiers in thoſe times.</p>
            <p>They cavil at the ſincerity of his Anſwers both by word of mouth and in writing to foreign Ambaſſadors, in the Affairs he had to concert with the Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> they tax him of too much Severity in the Execution of his Laws, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, againſt the Jews, and of too much adhering to particular Juſtice to the prejudice of the publick in the renuntiations he made to the Dutchy of <hi>Guien</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this noble Prince and Saint King <hi>Lewis</hi> better dealt with by the Catholick Hiſtorians, though perhaps not with ſuch an apparent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd prejudice, and that by Reaſon (for a more probable cauſe cannot be gueſs'd at) of that pragmatick Sanction which came forth under the Name of this Prince, occaſion'd by the quarrel he had with the Court of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36383:6"/>
               <hi>Rome.</hi> They look'd upon as Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal the zealous Concerns he had for the Rights of his Crown, and upon this pretence took upon them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatter all his actions without Limit or Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Of this laſt ſort of Writers ſome there are, who not daring to launch out into thoſe high Intemperancies, have yet fallen into another default equally diſadvantageous to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this Royal Saint. They have a conceit forſooth that there is no extraordinary Sanctity to be found but in Monaſteries, or at leaſt that it is not to be attain'd but by ſuch Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of the body as are there in uſe, and upon this preſuppoſal they carry on the main part of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign throughout all their Writings, ſo that they make it not ſo much their buiſineſs to repreſent this holy King <hi>Lewis</hi> ſuch as really he was, but ſuch as in their Opinion he ought to have been, that is to ſay, in ſtead of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36383:7"/>making him a great King as he was they ſet him forth a very Monk of the moſt reformed Order. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that in a Manuſcript Imbelliſht with curious Figures in Miniature which came to light about 12 years after his death, he is pourtray'd in ſeveral Exerciſes of Penitence, the moſt ſevere and bloody that were than practic'd in Cloiſters. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, one <hi>Richard</hi> a Monk of the <hi>Abby</hi> of <hi>Enove de Votsge,</hi> deſcribes him yielding to the Temptation of a certain <hi>Jacobin</hi> who urg'd him to take upon him the Order of St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick,</hi> and from which nothing but the powerful and inceſſant Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Queen his Mother, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the <hi>Hardy</hi> his Son, and <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Anjou</hi> his Brother could have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted him. <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> an Engliſh Benedictin, an Hiſtorian o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the moſt faithful and beſt informed of his Time, brings in our Princely St. <hi>Lewis</hi> at his reſtitution
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36383:7"/>of <hi>Guien</hi> to the Engliſh, uttering himſelf in a Speech no leſs void of Senſe then Regal Authority, and gives him a very lame at leaſt impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Character, when he tells us that without fear or reſpect of the Barons of his Realm he had given up to the Engliſh, thoſe other Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>August</hi> his Grandfather, had alienated from them in the Reign of King <hi>John,</hi> and reunited to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not all that hath been vented of unhandſome by theſe three above mentioned Authors, who all of them liv'd in the very Time of St. <hi>Lewis.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange to conſider how ſcant they are in recounting the Virtues of this Prince, as to his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Eſtate, how they bury, if I may ſo ſay, in myſterious ſilence the great Care he took to acquit himſelf handſomly of all things that belong'd to his Kingly Office? how they ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the beſt part of all his moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36383:8"/>glorious Actions, and ſpeak openly of thoſe only which were obſcurely ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther begun or ended? never conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this while that <hi>David</hi> in the midſt of all his plenty, and keeping a Court not differing in outward Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from that of other Kings, was yet a man no leſs at leaſt, if not more after Gods own heart than <hi>Racab,</hi> obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the utmoſt Severities of Life which the old Law requir'd. In fine, as if this Prince were deſtin'd to be the Mark of all Injuſtice, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hiſtorians have almoſt all of them in this point follow'd the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Ancients, whether it were that they only contented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to copy them out as it were, for want of the Originals by which they were to have been ſupplyed and mended, or, that they choſe rather to take upon Truſt what they found in Print, than to beſtow the pains and time to ſearch and conſult Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36383:8"/>
            <p>The deſign therefore of this work is to rectifie and turn to advantage the Miſtakes of others, and to remove thoſe Inconveniences that have enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them, at leaſt as far as can be done by touching upon them briefly, not having here time or place to repreſent all things in their full proportion; and I ſhall think my ſelf very happy, if without being wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I can handſomly make my way over ſo many Thorns, ſince doubtleſs there can be nothing more condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the Dolphins Inſtruction than to be preſented with a true Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of that perſon among all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, whoſe Life next to that of the Incomparable <hi>Lewis,</hi> the 14th. it moſt imports him to contemplate; and if I ſhould be ſo unhappy as not to ſucceed, I ſhall at leaſt gain this Advantage that the Correction of my Errors will inſtruct others more dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous to arrive at a ſafe Haven.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Lewis</hi> came into the World
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36383:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36383:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36383:10"/>the 25th. of <hi>April,</hi> in the Year, 1215: and thoſe who relate him born of a barren Mother, and make his Birth a Miracle wrought by the Prayers of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> are certainly ignorant that he had an Elder Brother call'd <hi>Philip,</hi> who dyed in his Minority. The Prince his Father liv'd till near 30 Years of Age a private Life, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting himſelf with the Kings Grace and Favour, and the hopes of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding him one day, when the Courſe of Nature and the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Law of the Land ſhould call him to the Crown. He was nam'd <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the aſtoniſhing fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Countenance in time of fight, which increas'd or diminiſh'd proportionally to the danger he was in procur'd him the Sirname of Lyon, however, he never reſembled this Animal but when he was engag'd in Military Affairs, being at other times the moſt obliging and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant of all men living; not to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36383:10"/>mention thoſe his other Excellencies which will afford a noble Character to him that ſhall undertake to write his Life: but in Relation to what hath been ſaid of him, one Inſtance of his Moderation cannot be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſince thereby was divulg'd upon the nobleſt Stage of <hi>Europe</hi> his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to perform the Command of God, who promiſeth a Reward both in this Life and that to come, to thoſe who give due Honour and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Parents.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> after the death of Queen <hi>Iſabel</hi> of <hi>Hainault</hi> his firſt Wife, by whom he had Prince <hi>Lewis,</hi> eſpouſed <hi>Angelberge</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> a Princeſs without Compare, the faireſt and moſt virtuous <hi>Europe</hi> could boaſt of. But the Inconſtancy of Man is never ſo deplorable as in ſuch like Conjunctures, wherein he changes in a moment not only from exceſs of love to exceſs of hatred, but which is worſe, from the exceſs of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36383:11"/>love to the utmoſt Indifference. <hi>Philip,</hi> the Morrow after his Nuptials with <hi>Angelberge,</hi> entertain'd a ſtrange averſion for her. He firſt excluded her from his Bed, next from his Houſe, He ſued out a Proceſs for the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Marriage and found the Biſhops ready enough to comply with his Reſolution upon pretext of an Imaginary kindred between the two Spouſes: upon their Sentence im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately enſued another Marriage of the King with <hi>Agnes</hi> of <hi>Tullet,</hi> other wiſe called <hi>Mary</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Bohemia</hi> by whom he had ſeveral Children: <hi>Angelberge</hi> bore her Divorce with a Patience never enough to be applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. She not only not oppos'd the Kings deſign, but forbore to return into her own Country, for fear her. Preſence ſhould animate her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Revenge the Affront ſhe had receiv'd. All the favour ſhe deſired was that ſhe might be permitted to reſide in <hi>France,</hi> where ſhe led ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36383:11"/>and retir'd a Life that all her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, her Rival her ſelf not excepted, could not but admire her, and pity her Condition.</p>
            <p>However, <hi>Canute</hi> King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> thought himſelf oblig'd in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, though ſhe oftentimes conjur'd him to the contrary, to appear for his Siſter <hi>Angelberge,</hi> and thereupon demanded juſtice in her behalf of Pope <hi>Celeſtin</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> inſomuch that his Holineſs remonſtrated the whole Affair to the King by Cardinal <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illeur,</hi> who not being admitted to a favourable hearing, addreſs'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Prelates that attended the Court, to little purpoſe God knows, for all the benefit he reapt of this Negotiation was a few inſignificant Expreſſions of their Compaſſion for the Queens Misfortune; and all his Eloquence, though he was accounted the beſt Oratour of his time, could not obtain one ſtep of advancement toward the reeſtabliſhment of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36383:12"/>Princeſs. The Cardinal upon this finding none to ſecond him, return'd to <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence the Pope, preſs'd by the continual Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>Danes,</hi> ſent ſoon after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France</hi> as his Legate, <hi>Peter</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of St. <hi>Mary</hi> with order to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Prelates of <hi>France,</hi> and to put the Realm under an Interdict, in caſe the King did not within a time prefixt receive <hi>Angelberge</hi> again. The Cardinal executed this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Commiſſion with as much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour as addreſs; and the King not doubting to come off by thoſe ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges that occur in formal Tryals conſented to the calling of a Councel at <hi>Dijon,</hi> the Capital Town of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie:</hi> the matter was examined to the bottom, and the juſteſt cauſe became the ſtrongeſt. Thoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of the Court Party who had pronounc'd the Marriage of <hi>Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> Null, either touch'd with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of Conſcience, or finding their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36383:12"/>Number not ſtrong enough to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, revok'd their Sentence, and the Council actuated by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, thundred out an Interdiction, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this Reſerve that twenty dayes reſpite ſhould be allow'd to the publication of their Decree,</p>
            <p>The King in ſtead of taking this limited Time to conſider of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, rather laid hold of an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, thereby to make his Appeal from the Determination of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and to revenge himſelf of the Biſhops who acted thus, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, with a malicious deſign of oppoſing his proceedings; he ſeis'd upon their Temporals, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Aſſiſtance they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from their Relations, for at that time the richeſt Benefices in <hi>France</hi> were in the hands of perſons of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt quality, he poſſeſs'd himſelf of the third part of Gentlemens Eſtates. In the next place, <hi>Angelberge</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from her preſent place of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36383:13"/>and confin'd to the Caſtle of <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> where ſhe was ſequeſtred from all Society, but only of ſuch as were the Creatures of her Rival.</p>
            <p>There were at that time in <hi>France</hi> ſcarce fewer Malecontents than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and though Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> could have no lawful cauſe for putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Head of them, yet never could he have had a fairer and more plauſible pretext: He had yet neither Place of Truſt nor Profit, neither Government of Town nor Province; all he had to ſubſiſt upon was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſumme of Money which he receiv'd yearly out of <hi>Spain.</hi> He could not hope to make his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion better while he kept himſelf in the Limits of due Obedience, whereas had he Headed the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, he might have aſſur'd himſelf of obtaining by Articles of Accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whatſoever he could have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd, for ſince thoſe People would never have been reduc'd without
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36383:13"/>him, the King muſt have been forc'd to have given them an entire Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor could he have avoided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things the taking back of <hi>Angelberge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all this while Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd firm and unſhaken in that Faith and Duty which he knew to be owing to his Father, and his King, and own'd himſelf bound in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Conſcience to adopt upon all accounts his Majeſties Intereſts as his own, and ſhewed a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Submiſſion at a time when all the reſt of his Subjects meditated a general Revolt; in ſhort, he gave an Example of Fidelity not to be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd in the Hiſtory of any Nation: Nor was this unexampled Loyalty of his long without a Recompence; for having ſo generouſly and virtuouſly refus'd an Illegal Power he was call'd to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal conſent of the Eſtates of the Realm. Three Years he there peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36383:14"/>reign'd, and when at the end thereof, the Inconſtancy of thoſe that had call'd him in unworthily retract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Allegeance which both their duty oblig'd them to, and his Virtue; Almighty God abundantly repair'd that detriment to him two ſeveral wayes, the one was a perpetual Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Crown of <hi>France</hi> upon his Poſterity from his Eldeſt Son, the other an Acceſſion of the Crowns of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> with the Earldom of Provence which fell contrary to all Expectation to the youngeſt of his Sons. But of the worldly Bleſſings that attended Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> there was none he made greater account of, or took higher Satisfaction in, than the Wife which God in his moſt eſpecial Providence beſtow'd upon him, <hi>viz. Blanch</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> Sirnamed the Noble, a Princeſs who in that rude, heavy Age wherein ſhe had the Misfortune
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36383:14"/>to be born, poſſeſs'd all thoſe graces which were capable to draw admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the moſt accompliſh'd La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of her time. And as none durſt diſpute the Prerogative of beauty with her, ſo it was abſolutely taken for confeſs'd on all hands that ſhe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſurpaſs'd them in a Noble and Gallant Meen. The young Age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe was Eſpous'd to <hi>Lewis,</hi> for ſhe was then ſcarce ripe for Marriage, render'd her ſo much the more pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and flexible in conforming to the humours and manners of the French Nation; wherein ſhe made ſo perfect an Improvement that ſhe could not poſſibly have been diſtinguiſh'd from a French Woman, but for that grave Severity which was too Natural to be eaſily quitted by her, though at a time when ſhe moſt reſign'd her ſelf up to Complaiſance and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, Her Air as Majeſtick as it was, had yet never any thing in it of diſobliging, being ever attended
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36383:15"/>with words and actions full of Spirit and Vivacity, and a Gaiety of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that infinitely became her: She enjoy'd ſo vigorous a health of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that till that ſickneſs took her which ended her dayes, ſhe never was troubled with any other diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than a ſhort quotidian Ague, which argued rather a ſtrong Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution then any Intemperature of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. Her beauty was not impair'd by Age, nor did the bringing of ten Children into the World any thing diminiſh the freſhneſs or delicacy of her Complexion. But that which ſingularly recommends her above all that hath been ſaid is the clear judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and exalted wit which ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her for buſineſs, that ſhe came not ſhort of the moſt eminent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Spain,</hi> either for quick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, or prudent forecaſt in the weightieſt Affairs without the leaſt of that heavy ſlowneſs and irreſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hath been the fault of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36383:15"/>as ſhe made appear by her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of thoſe no leſs difficult Tranſactions that hapned during her Regency, then have been known at any time; and with that Eaſe and diſpatch that ſhe was not obſerv'd to have the leaſt trouble or perplexity of Spirit. Her Piety was neither ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, nor a Cloak for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of any Intereſt, and it was an excellent ſaying of hers to her Children when ſhe had their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under her Care; That ſhe had rather ſee them buried than to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that purity of Life to which their Baptiſm had call'd them. Her Chaſtity was inviolable, however, that of all the reſt of her Virtues was moſt diſputed, both during her Life and after her death. The worſt that hath been ſaid of her in any of the moſt Satyrical Pieces that have toucht her in this tender point is, that ſhe gave too much pretence to Calumny. She entertain'd indeed a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36383:16"/>Principle more dangerous than could well conſiſt with a Ladies Honour, that is to ſay, that there are certain junctures which though rarely, might at ſome time or other happen, in which Ladies might lay aſide the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Formalities of Honour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they took care to preſerve it inviolable in the Main. This I ſay, Queen <hi>Blanch</hi> held for a Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Maxim of her Politicks, for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ſhe might without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſcience endeavour to give Love to any Prince or Potentate that could not by any other means be gain'd to her Intereſt; eſpecially, when it might prove a means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or put an end to a War or any inteſtine broil, to make an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof too many occaſions will offer themſelves in the Sequel of this Hiſtory; But in the firſt place, Foraſmuch as the Sentiments of the Queen in this matter were no way prejudicial to the Education of St.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36383:16"/>
               <hi>Lewis,</hi> it will he neceſſary before hand to ſhew how ſingular and ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly exact ſhe was in this matter.</p>
            <p>She undertook her ſelf the Office of Nurſe to this dear Son of hers, not thinking it ſafe, (for where moſt Love is, there is moſt jealouſie and ſuſpicion) he ſhould ſuck of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Milk than her own, upon this there hapned a <hi>Rencountre,</hi> which being not elſewhere to be found, though perhaps purpoſely omitted as beneath the Gravity of Hiſtory, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not handſomly be here paſs'd by. One day when ſhe had a violent hot fit of an Ague upon her, which alſo laſted longer than Ordinary, a Lady of Quality who either to pleaſe her Majeſty, or in imitation of her, had taken upon her to nurſe her own Son, being then preſent, and ſeeing the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Infant cry for the Teat, took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her the boldneſs to give him the Breaſt, the Queen when the fit was over, call'd for her Child, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36383:17"/>him her own Breaſt, but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant put it by, either, becauſe having ſuckt ſo lately he was fully ſatisfied, or, becauſe the freſh Milk he had lately taſted, made him the more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the burning heat of that which his Mother now offer'd him. The Reaſon was eaſie to be gueſs'd, and the Queen her ſelf ſuſpected what had hapned; She pretended an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient deſire of returning her thanks to the perſon who had oblig'd her by being ſo kind to her Child, during her Indiſpoſition; The Lady here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon expecting no doubt to be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, own'd what ſhe had done, and told the Queen that the crying of the Infant ſo ſenſibly touch'd her, that ſhe could not forbear to give it what Relief was in her power. But the Queen, inſtead of returning her the thanks ſhe expected, caſt a moſt diſdainful look upon her, and thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſinger into his mouth, forc'd him to give up all he hadreceiv'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36383:17"/>from her Breaſt. This violent Carriage of the Queen gave ſurpriſe to all that beheld it, whereupon, not to hold them long in ſuſpence, the Queen told them they ought not to think ſtrange of what they had ſeen, for that ſhe could not poſſibly endure that any Woman alive ſhould have a Right to diſpute with her the Quality of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo ſtedfaſt her perſwaſion was that the nurſing of Children is a great part of their Education.</p>
            <p>Other Particularities of the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> are not known, only in general it is not unknown, how great Care was taken to place ſuch perſons about him as were moſt capable to inſtruct him; but howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe perſons were, it may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any injuſtice to them, be ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſum'd their Abilities were not ſufficient for the high Province they were ſet in, it being in an Age when men of greateſt Fame for Literature were but very indifferently learned,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36383:18"/>and in a Kingdom whoſe Nobility at time lay under the ſcandal of that groſs Ignorance; beſides, that St. <hi>Lewis</hi> came too ſoon to the Crown to have that leiſure and opportunity which were neceſſary for a ſerious Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtudy. He was not above twelve years, and about ten dayes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, of Age, when his Father King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. who had not reign'd in <hi>France</hi> above three years, reſign'd him his place by an accident, whoſe Circumſtances have not been to this day ſufficiently made known.</p>
            <p>The moſt potent Feudatary of the French Monarchy, next to the King of <hi>England,</hi> was at that time <hi>Tibault</hi> the third, who <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> calls <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Champaign Brie, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres</hi> and <hi>Blois;</hi> the Sovereignty of which Eſtates had been in his Family above 400 Years, and it was no leſs then 300 Years ſince one of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors got himſelf immortal Fame by compelling the laſt King of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36383:18"/>(for the putting a ſtop to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution then on foot) to reſign his Crown to the Emperor <hi>Conrade.</hi> This Prince of all the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom of that time, had the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Alliances; his Mother being the Daughter and Heireſs of the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> his Grandmother Siſter of <hi>Philip,</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> King of <hi>France;</hi> his great Grandmother, Princeſs of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and her Mother of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Houſe of <hi>Suevia.</hi> He was of a large Stature, handſome, well made, valiant and active, Eſpecially, at the Exerciſe of the <hi>Lance,</hi> which was then an Exerciſe and Divertiſement much in uſe and Eſteem; but withal, he was extreamly ſubject to paſſions, which of all others are moſt incident to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his Quality and Grandure, and that in ſo high a degree, that it was hard to diſtinguiſh which was moſt predominant. He was born a young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Brother, but waited not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he became the Eldeſt, his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36383:19"/>dying without Male Iſſue, the Orphan Princeſſes he left behind found their Uncle inſtead of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor the greateſt Enemy and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor they had; Nor had he accepted of the Tuition of them, but only to gain an opportunity thereby of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading their Eſtates, which he delay'd no longer to do, then till he had made himſelf Maſter of all their ſtrong holds. The pretence he made uſe of to palliate his Injuſtice, was too weak to have ever been made uſe of before in the like Caſe; Namely, that the Earldoms of <hi>Champaign, Brie, Chartres</hi> and <hi>Blois</hi> were Fiefs purely Maſculine, that is to ſay, ſo firmly entail'd upon the Martial, or Arm-bearing Sex, as not to admit of any Woman whatſoever, though Married to the General of an Army.</p>
            <p>No leſs Criminal was this Earl in his amorous Inclination, nor did this paſſion of his tend leſs to evil Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, the reſpect he ow'd to <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36383:19"/>the 8th. his Sovereign, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he had of being ſo nearly rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, not reſtraining him from loving Queen <hi>Blanch</hi> beyond the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of honour and decency; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were that he gave way to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption equally with Love, or, that his Paſſion was moreover degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into folly; or, that he had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd an Opinion that Secrecy would more avail to the heighthning than ſuppreſſing of his Malady; or laſtly, that the Queens Virtue had driven him to deſpair; he not only took no care to hide the fury of his amorous Flame, but on the contrary ſought all extravagant ways imaginable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it to the World; he ſpent a great part of his time in making Love-ſongs, ſavouring more of a flaſhy wit than of a true Elegance, or Spirit of Poetry: theſe he made it his buſineſs to get preſented to the Queen, he caus'd them to be compos'd to Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and ſung to all ſorts of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36383:20"/>and either to keep them from growing out of date, as it generally happens when the Novelty of a thing is over, or, that their Memory of them might ſurvive both the Author and the Princeſs for whom they were made, he had them grav'd in Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and expos'd to the ſight of the whole world in the Galleries of his Palaces at <hi>Troye</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> as if he were afraid leaſt future Ages ſhould be unacquainted with his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the time he liv'd in ſhould want a fit Subject for <hi>Satyre.</hi> Such was the exceſſive heighth of his Imprudence, which the King was not then in a Condition to chaſtiſe, he thought it better to pretend Ignorance, than to manifeſt his weakneſs by unprofitable marks of Anger. The Engliſh were then in Arms for the recovery of thoſe French Provinces which <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> had taken from them, and <hi>France</hi> could not have hindred, had the Forces which were rais'd to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36383:20"/>oppoſe them been diſunited: He ſtood in need of the Aid of all his Feuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries; and the revolt of this Count alone had been enough to ruine the whole deſign. Thus was the King conſtrain'd to carry himſelf toward his Rival, as Criminal as he was, and the Event prov'd that his Majeſty had taken, if not the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet at leaſt the moſt profitable Expedient. The Earl, who was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſufficiently Valiant, had brought a conſiderable Addition to the French Army, of choice Troops, all conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Vaſſals, and fought like a true Lover of that Age, that is to ſay, he had the Vanity to expoſe himſelf to the greateſt of dangers for the Love of his Lady; The Engliſh whom he was the forwardeſt to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque, were driven to ſtand upon their deſence; and the Towns of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ort,</hi> and St. <hi>John d'Angeli,</hi> which they had lately recover'd, were again ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them by force; the Town
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36383:21"/>of <hi>Rochel,</hi> to avoid plundering, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the French; ſo that at laſt the Engliſh, diſheartned by ſo many misfortunes, were glad of a Truce. The King was the more willing to agree to it, as deſirous to loſe no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion for the reuniting to his Realm the largeſt of thoſe Provinces which had been diſſever'd from it ever ſince the declining of the ſecond Race.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon</hi> Earl of <hi>Monfort</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt fortunate Captain of his Age, had gain'd <hi>Languedoc</hi> from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral petty <hi>Albigenſian</hi> Princes, who at that time had poſſeſs'd it; but <hi>Amaureus</hi> his Son could not keep it, the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> recover'd again the beſt part of it, and <hi>Amaureus</hi> choſe rather to give up the reſt for the Conſtable's Staff of <hi>France,</hi> than to ſtand out till he was depriv'd of all without any Recompence. He had yielded up his Right to the moſt Chriſtian King, and his Majeſty being engag'd in this War, as well for his own proper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36383:21"/>as thoſe of Religion, had a Rendezvous in <hi>Berry</hi> of all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he could bring together, as well his own as thoſe of his Feudataries, with which he ſate down before the Town of <hi>Avignon,</hi> where the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> after they were forc'd to quit the Field, had brought the choice of all their Troops.</p>
            <p>There was no want in the Town either of Proviſion, or any warlike Accomodations which were then in uſe, nor were the French without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof, yet they deſiſted not from attacquing the place, but by Reaſon of the death of the famous <hi>Guy</hi> Earl of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to whom they had been oblig'd for the victory of <hi>Bovines,</hi> and of the wounding of 4000 of their men, beſides, 2000 more ſlain in the ditches, they were forc'd to change the Siege into a <hi>Blockade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Beſieged for all this were ſoon brought to a Capitulation, and the King found therein the Keys of all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36383:22"/>the <hi>Albigenſian</hi> Towns, except thoſe of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> the Year was too far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd and the Souldiers too much tir'd to begin a new Siege: Beſides, it was impoſſible the French Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry could ſubſiſt about <hi>Tholouſe</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> had plough'd all the Meadows thereabout. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it was thought expedient not to lye at too great a diſtance from the place, for two ſeveral Reaſons, the one, to hinder the Spaniards from drawing together thoſe ſuccours which they had promis'd to the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi> the other, becauſe the French Army conſiſting chiefly of thoſe Troops which the Feudataries of the Crown had levied, had they been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to march home; the Spring and the beſt part of Summer (ſo tardy muſt their return have been by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the length of the way) would have been gone before, they could have turn'd to the Siege of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi> Upon this account it was that the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36383:22"/>King reſolv'd to take up his Winter Quarters in the Neighbouring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and had his Head-quarters at <hi>Mont</hi>— a Caſtle ſcituate upon the Frontiers of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne.</hi> The deſign was new, there had ſcarce been any Example thereof, ſince the Reign of the third Race in <hi>France,</hi> however, it might have been the occaſion of ſhrew'd Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Feudataries had infallibly oppos'd it, ſhould the King have gone about to put it in execution, without having firſt obtain'd their conſent in a Council of War.</p>
            <p>It was in a full Council that the King diſcours'd them concerning this Affair, but in ſuch Terms as on the one ſide repreſented how abſolutely neceſſary it was for the whole Army to quarter in thoſe places, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, teſtified the high Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ſhould take in gaining their Conſents, he wanted but little of his deſire, all the Feudataries gave their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36383:23"/>hands except the Earl of <hi>Champaign:</hi> the Queen then reſided at <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Court was no longer able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure her abſence. He thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſure of ſeeing her within a very ſhort time. And you may well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how it would reliſh with the moſt impatient of all men living, to meet with a freſh <hi>Rencountre,</hi> that ſhould debar him the ſight of his Miſtreſs a whole Year longer. Thus netled therefore as he was, I am not ſaid he, in a full Council, againſt the Complaiſance of the reſt of the <hi>Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dataries,</hi> but for my own part, I think it juſt, to ſtand ſo far upon my Rights and Priviledges, as to draw off my Troops into <hi>Brie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Anſwer ſeem'd to proceed from nothing but a haughty, proud Reſolution, but the King was not ſo ſlow of apprehenſion as not to pierce into the true Reaſon. His Majeſty had juſt cauſe enough of anger againſt him upon ſuch an occaſion, as had the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36383:23"/>reſt follow'd his Example, might have prov'd of fatal Conſequence, and left him abandon'd of all; nor could he refrain from reproaching the Earl for this Affront, and threatning him, if he perſiſted longer in theſe Expreſſions, to fall into his Territories with Fire and Sword. The Earl who hated the King no leſs than he lov'd the Queen, pretended that his Majeſty ought to have ſhew'd ſome kind of reſpect toward him, and have treated him rather as an Equal, than as a Vaſſal, ſince he was Heir to a Crown; that he ought to take notice of thoſe Menaces as ſerious, and not words of Courſe, conſidering what extremity the Kings obſtinate humour had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported him to, he being too exact an obſerver of his word in ſuch Caſes. It was indeed above an Age ſince <hi>Brie</hi> and <hi>Champaign</hi> had been abſolutely free from all the Calamities of War, and ſuch was the plenty in general of the whole Country, that the French
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36383:24"/>Army might have found very good Quarters there, had it ſtood with the Intereſt of the Kings Affairs. This Crime was the moſt hainous of any the Earl had been yet tax'd with, but it will appear by what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid, that he was no Novice in committing the blackeſt of Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Moreover, his imagination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated by the different paſſions which had got the Maſtery of him, began to entertain an Idea of Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide as of abſolute neceſſity at this time.</p>
            <p>He could not reſolve upon at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the Kings Life by open force, at a time when he had all his Troops about him, nor was the way of Aſſaſſination much more ſafe; It was now many Ages ſince any of the French Monarchs had been taken off by this way, ſo ready the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had been to take part with them, and to revenge all deſigns whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put in practice againſt. them.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:36383:24"/>
            <p>No way was left but poiſon, and the French, who from the very firſt beginning of the Monarchy, had had this practice in the greateſt deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, began inſenſibly to have an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to it, whether it were that they were of late grown more Ingenious in Malice, or that they had learn'd this way of giving their Enemies a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, either from the Infidels againſt whom they had born Arms, or from the Greeks with whom they had of late been more than formerly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. What kind of poiſon it was that the Earl gave the King was never ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely diſcovered, but ſure enough, for the greater Secrecy of the matter, ſuch a Doſe was given him as caus'd a lingring diſtemper. The King diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled for many dayes the violence of the Feavour which inwardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fum'd him, nor did he to the very laſt ſo much reſent the pain he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd, as the diſturbances likely to enſue as to publick Affairs; Jealouſy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36383:25"/>for its greater Satisfaction finds out peculiar wayes of taking Vengeance. The Earl had the pleaſure before he parted to ſee the King languiſhing on his death bed, and to foreſee that his leaving him in that Condition would augment his grief and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Spirit. However, he had the confidence for all this to go and wait upon the Queen, as preſuppoſing that ſhe could hardly ſuſpect the true cauſe of her Husbands Malady; or at leaſt, if ſhe ſhould come to under-it, ſhe would be oblig'd to conceal her knowledge, becauſe of the need ſhe would have of his aſſiſtance in obtaining the Regency; Nor was it long e're the King finding his end to draw near, made his Will, in which he appointed the Queen to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs of her Eldeſt Son, and Regent of the Kingdom. He dyed theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>November,</hi> 1226, in the 39th. Year of his Age, This laſt Will and Teſtament met with no oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36383:25"/>on; whether it were that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Blood and Nobility of the Realm were wrought upon by thoſe pathetical diſcourſes which he made to them upon his death bed, to oblige them to purſue his Intereſts; or, that their wavering minds had not yet fix'd upon thoſe meaſures which were to be taken for a Revolt intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or, had they indeed been ready for any ſuch deſign, they were watch'd too narrowly by the Queen to bring it to Effect; For, notwithſtanding ſhe was left a Widow at a Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture capable of diſheartning a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who, though of wit and ſpirit enough, yet wanted two qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which might render a womans Government ſupportable to the French Nation, that is to ſay, Credit and Experience; however, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd by all means poſſible to inform her ſelf of the Genius of a People ſhe was to govern, and eafily apprehended that the beſt way to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36383:26"/>prevent what ever deſigns might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be broach'd in <hi>France,</hi> was to carry with all ſpeed her Eldeſt Son St. <hi>Lewis</hi> to <hi>Reims,</hi> to be there anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King; and that nothing would ſo much conduce as this Ceremony to keep within the bounds of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance a People, prepoſſeſs'd with an opinion of his being hereby made a partaker in the Sovereign Power. The extraordinary haſte that was made for the King's Journy into <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign,</hi> hinder'd the Grandees and Nobles from accompanying the King with the Splendor and Magnificence uſual upon ſuch occaſions, notice on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was given, that the King was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to diſpence with the trouble and charge of thoſe great preparations, expecting their Attendance in perſon only without any pompous Train, or numerous Retinue, which in ſuch an Affair as this would be but trouble-ſome and apt to breed diſturbance. This Ceremony was perform'd in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36383:26"/>beginning of <hi>December</hi> 1226, by the Miniſtry of the Biſhop of <hi>Soiſſons, Premier Suffragan</hi> of the Archbiſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick of <hi>Reims,</hi> whoſe ſeat was then vacant. But <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the Kings Paternal Uncle, firſt Prince of the Blood, Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> and <hi>Clermont,</hi> whether it were that he took Exception to ſee himſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded by the Peers of <hi>France,</hi> at the Kings Inauguration, or, becauſe the Regent had not confirm'd the Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of his <hi>Appenage,</hi> which was promis'd him when he gave his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to her being made Regent, what ever it were he repented him of what he had done when it was but juſt too late to revoke it; He was the firſt man that labour'd to deſtroy his own work though no man was more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd than himſelf to preſerve it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire. He came ſhort in deeds of Arms both of his Father and his Brother, but equall'd them both in wit, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd them in Vigour and Addreſs:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36383:27"/>and though there were no other proofs then the Intreagues hereafter mention'd, they are ſufficient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him the moſt ſubtle, and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Prince of his Age. He repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, both by word of mouth and by writing, to all the Nobles of the Realm, how they had been circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, how that a Spaniſh Woman had found a way how to deprive them of the fruit of all their labours, and that notwithſtanding thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts which had been gain'd by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the <hi>August</hi> in a War of 50 Years, to avoid falling under the Engliſh Power, and the coming off with ſo much glory in ſo difficult an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, they were now in danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under that Yoke whereof in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times they had ſo univerſal a dread; That the Queen whom they had declar'd Regent, was indeed born in a Country which hitherto had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Antipathy nor Intereſt with <hi>France,</hi> but that ſhe was in Effect
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36383:27"/>Engliſh, and neither could, nor ought to be conſider'd as others wiſe, though at a time when ſhe took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her the Government of the French. That ſhe was the daughter of <hi>Eleanor,</hi> Princeſs of <hi>England,</hi> and Grandchild of a Queen of the ſame Name, who had detach'd <hi>Guien</hi> from the Crown of <hi>France</hi> to unite it to <hi>England.</hi> That though ſhe was the daughter of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> (ſirnamed the Noble) King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> yet ſhe was not married to the late King <hi>Lewis</hi> as <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> but as Princeſs of the Royal Houſe of <hi>England,</hi> where the Daughters are call'd to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Crown for want of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Male. That this Marriage had been reſolv'd on in a ſolemn Treaty with the Engliſh. That the King of <hi>England</hi> had endow'd her with the Earldom of <hi>Eureux,</hi> and 30000 Marks of Silver, and therefore had reaſon to expect from her a Recompence proportionable to the eſtabliſhment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36383:28"/>he had ſetled upon her. That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs could be expected but giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back the Provinces conquer'd from King <hi>John Lackland,</hi> which would be to the prejudice even of thoſe Children which ſhe had brought into the World.</p>
            <p>That it was the Regent's humour to deſire rather to be accounted an ill natur'd than an ungrateful Perſon, that this only conſideration was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to render her unworthy of the adminiſtration of the French Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; but that there was another al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo no leſs apparent, nor no leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable which was this: The late King had form'd a deſign, and put a good beginning to it of uniting <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedock</hi> to the Crown, the chief ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to which by reaſon of his Majeſties untimely death, would be the not taking of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, beſides, that ſhe was uncapable of ſuch an Enterpriſe, being too much concern'd as a Native of <hi>Spain,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36383:28"/>by all means poſſible the growth of the French Monarchy on the <hi>Pirenean</hi> ſide, not to put off the Siege to another time, under pretence of the Minority of the King her Son, when ever ſhe ſhould be conſtrain'd to undergo the Importunities that muſt needs be made to her upon this account, that the only Remedy to prevent theſe two Inconveniences would be to depoſe the Queen from her Regency, and to put in her ſtead a Prince who on the one ſide ſhould have no obligation to the Engliſh, and on the other ſide would be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of commanding the Army de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for the taking of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Harangue</hi> which the Earl made uſe of in the Nature of a <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſto,</hi> laid down nothing which in the main was not exactly true, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al it was enfeebled by a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too plain to be unperceiv'd. In the beginning of his diſcourſe, he preſuppoſes her Engliſh, deſigning
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36383:29"/>thereby to raiſe an Odium againſt her upon the account of the Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe muſt needs have for <hi>France,</hi> on the contrary, at the latter end, he will have her a Native of <hi>Spain</hi> on purpoſe to render her ſuſpected, and uncapable of purſuing the Conqueſt of <hi>Languedock.</hi> However, this Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had almoſt all the ſucceſs the Earl could promiſe himſelf from it, ſince thereby he engag'd to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the two ſorts of People which were then of moſt Credit in <hi>France,</hi> that is to ſay, thoſe who had a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary paſſion for the Grandure of that Monarchy, and thoſe who leſs ſoaring in Ambition, pleas'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with the thought that this would be a great means of rooting out the Hereticks, and were carried on with wonderful Application to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Conqueſt of <hi>Languedock,</hi> as imagining it another holy War; Of this number were the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the Earls of <hi>March,</hi> St.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36383:29"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar;</hi> whoſe Aſſociation was of great importance to the Earl of <hi>Boulogne,</hi> and ſo much the more for that they thought themſelves tied to his Intereſts by the ſtrongeſt of humane Bonds to wit, Zeal, no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whether true orfalſe.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſecur'd thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſerve him out of pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, he made it his next buſineſs to gain thoſe who act in all things as humour or intereſt leads them: of this ſort of perſons the Earl of <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne</hi> was the firſt he addreſs'd himſelf to. This Prince found not that return of Love from the Queen which he thought his Services merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor was he very much ſurpris'd thereat, whether it were that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the Queens Inſenſibility to thoſe impreſſions which the ſurviving Love of her deceas'd Husband had left in her heart, or that he believ'd the caſe of her Honour oblig'd her to keep within the bounds of exact
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36383:30"/>decorum, at a time when ſhe knew the Eyes of the whole world would be upon her: but he was more throughly convinc'd of the vanity of perſiſting in his Love, when he ſaw that the Queen, after ſhe had taken upon her the Regency, treated him no otherwiſe than common Civility oblig'd her to, and that ſhe neglect-him ſo far as not to make him a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the Government by giving him a place in the Council of State: his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient humour ſtirr'd him up to high complaints of her ſlighting Uſage. Whereupon the Earl of <hi>Bologne</hi> who was neither ignorant of his Amours, nor his ill ſucceſs therein, concluded the beſt way to draw him to a Revolt, would be to heighten his jealouſie.</p>
            <p>The Pope had ſent <hi>Legate</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> a Prelate altogether agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that Court: he was call'd <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manor,</hi> being a Native of <hi>Rome</hi> of the loweſt rank of the Populacy; nevertheleſs, he was endu'd with ſuch
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36383:30"/>qualities as made him appear a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of real Grandure in all places wherever he came: he had an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſhape of body, and for a gallant Meen was not equall'd by any; his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate and quick parts made him paſs for a Miracle of wit, and the rather for that it was very rare in that Age. In fine, all <hi>Europe</hi> could not boaſt ſo compleat a Courtier: to him <hi>France</hi> ow'd the Conqueſts that had been made in <hi>Languedock;</hi> for it was he that call'd the Council at <hi>Bourges,</hi> wherein the continuation of the war againſt the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> was decreed; he that had diſpos'd all the Nobility of the Realm to ſerve in this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition at their own Charge; he that had excommunicated anew the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> he that took off the Fathers of the Councel from ſhewing him any favour, when he came in as a penitent at a time when they leaſt expected it. This induc'd the Queen to have a particular reſpect
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36383:31"/>for the Legate, whether mov'd by the meer conſideration of his Merits, or thinking her ſelf oblig'd to treat with more than ordinary Civilities a Miniſter of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and one whoſe aſſiſtance ſhe mainly ſtood in need of to compleat the Conqueſt of <hi>Languedock,</hi> and to keep the <hi>French</hi> in ſubjection and obedience during ſo long a Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; She conſulted him in all impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant affairs, follow'd his advice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others, and of thoſe paſſant Civilities he deſir'd for any of his friends ſhe deny'd him none; theſe things added ſo much to the count of <hi>Champaign</hi>'s jealouſie, that the Malecontents could have wiſht for no better opportunity to bring him over to their Party.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> repreſented to him that he ought in reaſon to diſengage his heart from a Spaniſh woman, who had been ſo laviſh of hers as to part with it to a Prieſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36383:31"/>and that he could not in honour have any other Sentiments for her, than thoſe of abhorrence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, for the injury ſhe did to the Memory of her deceas'd Husband. There is nothing a man inclines to. more than to believe things areas he would have them.</p>
            <p>The Earl how ever was at a loſs, and knew not what to think of her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of treating him; he could not imagine that ſo young and fair as ſhe was, ſhe could confine her ſelf all her life long to a languiſhing and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Widow-hood, having an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſhe might be glad to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, of enjoying in ſecond Nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als the Heir preſumptive of the Crown of <hi>Navarre;</hi> ail this while he ſaw plainly that this Princeſs had no diſpoſition to make him happy, though to her own advantage; and ſince he could not dive into the true cauſe, and was not ſatisfied with any of thoſe he revolved in his mind; he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36383:32"/>fix'd upon that which had been ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to him, never examining the probability of it, or conſidering that it was infinitely more ridiculous than any thing he could imagine beſide.</p>
            <p>Thus imputing the Queens indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference for him, to the love which it was ſurmiſed ſhe had for the Legate; upon this ſullen ſuppoſition he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd upon the ſuppreſſing of a paſſion, with which he was even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to burſt. Upon this he entred into the Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi>'s Party, and drew along with him his Brother of Arms, <hi>Hugo de Dampmartin,</hi> Count of <hi>Ponthieu,</hi> whoſe Eldeſt Brother was <hi>Renald,</hi> Count of <hi>Dampmartin, Auſcon, Iſlebon,</hi> and <hi>Domfront.</hi> He having married the Niece of King <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>August,</hi> took the boldneſs and Authority upon him, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of this Alliance to beſiege, and having taken it, to raſe down to the ground a Caſtle belonging to the Biſhop of <hi>Beauvais,</hi> a Prince of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36383:32"/>blood, and Couſin German to the ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>August,</hi> who, glad of an occaſion to bring down this Count of <hi>Dampmartin,</hi> whom he knew to be the moſt turbulent and dangerous perſon of his whole Realm, took ſpeedy courſe with him, and confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated all his Eſtate. The Earl thus reduc'd from his former heighth to a dependance upon others for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, was forc'd at laſt to beg the Kings pardon, but in vain; for all the Anſwer he could obtain of the King was, that though he had no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to give an account of his actions to any one whatſoever, yet nevertheleſs, he was content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the hearing of all matters in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie to the Chamber Royal, and the Barons of the Realm.</p>
            <p>But this propoſal reliſh'd not at all with the Earl, for beſides that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected no other than to be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they ſhould proceed to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rigour againſt him; he knew
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36383:33"/>well enough the power and credit his Majeſty had in that Court where he was to plead. So that ſeeing no other remedy, he took part with the Engliſh, and had the misfortune to be taken with other Priſoners at the Battel of <hi>Bovines,</hi> where he had lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd out a long Confinement, though in a ſpatious Priſon, of about 22 Years, his Brother the Earl of <hi>Ponthieu</hi> not being able to procure his Releaſement. And indeed the two laſt Kings, <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. and after them the Regent, had ever held it as a ſure Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Maxim, that it very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to keep in durance all his life time, that Vaſſal of theirs who was moſt potent and formidable, ſo long as there was any advantage to he taken without any abſolute viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice; ſo that there was no probability of this Earls deliverance but by force of Arms. The Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> promis'd <hi>Ponthieu</hi> to act
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36383:33"/>with all the vigour requiſite upon ſuch an occaſion for the ſetting his Brother free; and that if it were not done before the Overtures of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of peace, the ſaid Treaty ſhould never be concluded but upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he were firſt releas'd</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> being thus aſſur'd of thoſe Feudataries who were neareſt about the heart of the French Monarchy, made it his next deſign to gain thoſe who were more remote, and more eſpecially addreſs'd himſelf to <hi>Jane</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Hainault.</hi> This Princeſs was married to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Infant of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> and Eldeſt Son of King <hi>Sanchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who according to the Cuſtome of the <hi>Cadets</hi> of noble Families, had ſought his Fortune in <hi>France,</hi> and behav'd himſelf like one of thoſe old Knights errant ſo renown'd in Story; and in truth he lighted upon better fortune than ever he could have hop'd for. <hi>Balduin</hi> Emperor of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36383:34"/>
               <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> dying without Iſſue Male, had left King <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> Tutor to his daughter Princeſs <hi>Jane,</hi> with power to marry her to whom he thought fit. The King having a good opinion of <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi>'s Merit; or, elſe not willing to beſtow her upon a French man, for fear of making him too potent, match'd her to this Portugueſs, who had not made his pretenſion to her, but as reſolving to ſtand in Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with any pretenders whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though their hopes were built upon never ſo much better a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But no ſooner was <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> by this Match become Maſter of two Eſtates, more conſiderable at that time than the Crown of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> it ſelf, but he ſtain'd his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a moſt horrible Ingratitude. He ſuffer'd himſelf to be deluded by the ſame <hi>Renald de Dampmartin,</hi> whom we have already mention'd, ſo far as to bear Arms for the Engliſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36383:34"/>againſt his Benefactor; for which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly he had the ſame fate, being likewiſe taken Priſoner at <hi>Bovines,</hi> after he had receiv'd ſix wounds in the body by the valiant <hi>Hugode Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revil,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Xaintogne.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, his being taken Priſoner, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him nothing near ſo much as the courſe they took with him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; for the King, who knew him to be the proudeſt Prince of that Age, knew alſo what would moſt touch him to the quick, and bring down the pride of his haughty heart; he caus'd him to be led in Triumph through the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> in which diſgraceful march he was ſaluted with ſuch kind of Language as the Mobile commonly beſtow upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his Circumſtance. After he had been kept for ſome time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other hopes than of perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Impriſonment, it was thought fit to give him up a Freeman to the tears and ſubmiſſions of his Wife,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36383:35"/>who was come to caſt her ſelf at the Kings feet, and to let him live in peace, only all the ſtrong places of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Hainault</hi> were to be ras'd to the ground. Hereupon, he was ſhortly to have been releas'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Geoffry</hi> Son of the Earl of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> his ſtanding ſurety for him; but whether it were that <hi>Geoffry</hi> refus'd to yield to that clauſe of the Treaty, or, that the King had taken freſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure from any words <hi>Ferdinand</hi> had let fall ſince this Negotiation, he was ſtill kept a Priſoner, and his Wife thus fruſtrated of her hopes of ſeeing him again at liberty, yielded to the firſt invitation made to her of entring into the League; The Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> encourag'd by this ſo ſpeedy and proſperous ſucceſs, made his next Addreſs to two Brothers Princes of the Blood, <hi>viz. Peter</hi> Duke of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Dreux:</hi> As for the Duke of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taign,</hi> he was no leſs oblig'd to the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36383:35"/>Crown of <hi>France,</hi> then the Earl of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and his Ingratitude was of no leſs tendency to the violation of all Right and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding of an Entreague which hath not been ſufficiently made known, neither in the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> nor of any other Nation, it is to be noted, that <hi>Rollando,</hi> the firſt Duke of <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> compell'd by force of Arms, the firſt Earl of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> to do him Homage for his Earldom, in the ſame manner as the Dukes of <hi>Normandy</hi> have ſince done Homage for their Dutchies to the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Bretaign</hi> became an <hi>arrier-fief</hi> to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> In this State it continued till the death of <hi>Covan</hi>—Earl of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> who left Iſſue only one daughter nam'd <hi>Conſtance.</hi> This rich Heireſs was courted by many, but <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>England</hi> pretended, as Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the Right of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36383:36"/>Marriage, and partly, by his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, partly, by his Addreſſes of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, obtain'd her, and had four Sons by her, <hi>Henry, Richard, Geoffry,</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> He deſign'd to leave to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> to <hi>Richard</hi> the Provinces of <hi>Normandy, Main, Anjou,</hi> and <hi>Tourain,</hi> which fell to him by Succeſſion from his Father and Mother, and the Provinces of <hi>Guien,</hi> and <hi>Poictou,</hi> which he had in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age by his former Wife <hi>Eleanor.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two young Princes and the two daughters of the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 7th. there was a ſolemn Treaty of Marriage, and the King of <hi>England</hi> had Intereſt enough to bring both to effect. <hi>John</hi> his 4th Son was deſign'd for Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Preferment; ſo that a Match having been propos'd between the Heireſs of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>England,</hi> ſhe muſt now of neceſſity be married, if to any, to <hi>Geoffry</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi>'s third Son. In fine, the was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36383:36"/>married to him upon conſiderations meerly Political, for his perſon was no way taking with the young Lady; but his death ſoon deliver'd her, and left her to a ſecond Marriage more to her content; for ſhe her ſelf then made choice of <hi>Guy de Thouars,</hi> a Knight, the handſomeſt and braveſt perſon of his Age, by whom ſhe had but one daughter; her firſt Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had left her big with Child of a Son nam'd <hi>Arthur,</hi> whoſe death was the more unhappy, for that he was depriv'd thereby of ſuch an accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Succeſſions; that of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Provinces there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appendant, fell to him by the death without Iſſue of his Fathers two Eldeſt Brothers; and <hi>Bretaign</hi> being his at the ſame time in Right of his Mother, he had doubtleſs in proſpect, had he liv'd, the vaſteſt Monarchy that had been known ſince the partage of the Imperial Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; but <hi>John</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:36383:37"/>ſirnamed <hi>Lackland</hi> the only Uncle, who ſurviv'd, procur'd his death to get his Eſtate, and by this means the daughter of <hi>Guy de Thouars,</hi> became ſole Heireſs of the Earldom of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taign. Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt,</hi> who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king advantage of the villany of <hi>John Lackland,</hi> had reunited the Dutchy of <hi>Normandy</hi> to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> pretended that ſince <hi>Henry</hi> theſe cond, King of <hi>England,</hi> had power as being Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> to diſpoſe of the Mother, he both as Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and King of <hi>France</hi> together, had ſo much the better Title to diſpoſe of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The branch of <hi>Dreux</hi> was at that time the moſt proper branch of the Royal Family: his appennage was ſmall, he had neither Office nor Government, his Alliances had not enrich'd him, and it was to be fear'd he might loſe his Rank for want of Eſtate; as it hapned ſome time ſince, to the branch of <hi>Cortenai,</hi> ſuppoſing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36383:37"/>his publih'd Genealogy be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exact. This made <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> the more willing to give the Heireſs of <hi>Bretaign</hi> to <hi>Peter de Dreux,</hi> with this Condition, that <hi>Bretaign</hi> ſhould henceforth be immediately held of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> that is to ſay, that it ſhould no more do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to whoever ſhould be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Normandy,</hi> in caſe that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſhould ever be again diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred from the Crown. The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was advantagious to both the new married Parties, ſince their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates were now no longer held in <hi>arrier fiefs;</hi> nor would depend for the time to come upon a ſingle Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> but only upon the firſt of Chriſtian Kings. Nor did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one receive prejudice by it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <hi>Normandy</hi> was reunited to the Crown. No wonder then if <hi>Peter de Dreux</hi> and his Wife accepted gladly the Condition, and obſerv'd it in all particulars. But that ſoon befel the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36383:38"/>new Duke of <hi>Bretaign</hi> which is but too frequent with men of ſlender virtue, that is to ſay, he ſuffer'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be drawn away, and tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this flowing Tide of good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. The large Extent of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and its advantageous Situation, gave it a very ſufficient Title, and Merit in this Princes opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to an abſolute and independent Sovereignty; beſides, he was pleas'd to flatter himſelf with this conceit that his carrying on ſo high a deſign, as the ſhaking of the French yoke, would immortalize his Name to all Poſterity: which great undertaking, the better to accompliſh, he was real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded that his ſiding with the Earl of <hi>Boulogne,</hi> and his Party, was as fair an opportunity as he could have wiſht for, taking it for granted, that if the Earl ſucceeded, he could do no leſs than remit his homage of <hi>Bretaign</hi> in recompense of his decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for him; In caſe he did not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36383:38"/>the Regent in revenge, that ſhe might oblige thoſe Princes of the blood, who had taken part with him, to deſert him, would be glad to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to what ever they ſhould demand of her. Thus the Duke of <hi>Bretaign</hi> turn'd Rebel upon falſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, with which he fed his fancy; but the moſt croſs and untoward oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in his Revolt, was his draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon a quite contrary princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Brother <hi>Robert de Dreux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Perſon had a Soul ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of all benefits, and ſo prone to grateful returns, that he thought he could not better teſtifie the high ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation he had to the Duke of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taign,</hi> for having left entire to him the Apennage of their branch, than by ſerving him for, or, againſt whom ſoever he deſir'd, except the King. Thus he put himſelf under the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Malecontents, by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive the moſt excuſable that ever was, if any excuſe can be admitted in matters of Treaſon.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36383:39"/>
            <p>The laſt Prince of the blood that the Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi> drew in to his Party, was <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Courtenay,</hi> whom he found the more pliable to his Temptations by diſcontent, becauſe, the branch of the <hi>Dreux</hi> had been preferr'd before his by the Match of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and to engage him the more deeply, he had opportunity given him to make himſelf Maſter of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſumms of the Kings mony.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raimond</hi> the 7th of that Name, Earl of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> ſirnamed the young, was before hand with the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, to whom without ſtaying for any Invitation from them, he went and joyned of his own accord, upon the firſt proſpect he had of a civil war. His main inducement to this proceeding, for he had none of thoſe pretences which the reſt made uſe of, was only to ſave himſelf by fiſhing in other mens troubled waters. The Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Thunders ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd without Exception all thoſe pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36383:39"/>Princes upon whom they lighted, was altogether inexorable toward this Prince, and would not quit him of thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures which had been pronounc'd againſt him, though the refuſal thereof was the greateſt obſtacle to the recovery of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> This Interdiction had ſo powerful an aſcendant upon his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects minds, that they thought they might be very well excus'd from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging him their Prince, with whom they were forbidden to have any Communication or Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, inſomuch, as all the relief and aſſiſtance he could get, was from thoſe infected with the Albigenſian Hereſie. This ſort of people were at that time not ſo numerous as the Catholicks; and ſhould the Regent take <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> the Capital City of that Country, there would be no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Counts reeſtabliſhment. So that by thus engaging himſelf with the Malecontents, he thought on the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36383:40"/>one ſide let the worſt come to the worſt, he could not be more unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate than he was in that wretched Eſtate to which hehad been reduc'd; on the other ſide, the leaſt ſucceſs ſhould attend his Party would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the recovery of his loſt Eſtate. The Earl of <hi>Provence,</hi> a Prince e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually conſiderable, and his Couſin of the houſe of <hi>Catalogue,</hi> came in laſt of the French into the Earl of <hi>Bolognes</hi> Party, led by Motives which only concern'd him at a diſtance; for he had no reaſon to complain either of the moſt Chriſtian Kings in general, or, of the Regent in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, againſt whom he could be no otherwiſe incens'd, than by thoſe too deep reflections he made upon what might happen for the future, the French as he thought, border'd too near upon <hi>Provence,</hi> their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood rendred them ſuſpected to him; when the French had a victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious King at the head of them, his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36383:40"/>fear of being entangled in his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins Ruine kept him back from aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him againſt them; but after that this Warlike Prince was taken off by Death, he thought, that though he could not yet with ſafety pluck off his Vizard quite, and have recourſe to open Arms in defence of the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> who was yet but half ejected, he might at leaſt ſecurely act under-hand, ſo as to engage them the ſooner in a Civil War, which was in a manner already begun, to the end, he might give Advantage to the ſaid Earl to recover <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc,</hi> without being Oblig'd to any one but himſelf.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of the Princes and Nobility of <hi>France</hi> being thus corrupted by the Artifices above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, the Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi>'s Faction was in all appearance ſtrong enough not to ſtand in need of the help of ſtrangers, yet nevertheleſs it was reſolv'd no Aids ſhould be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36383:41"/>refus'd, of how little neceſſity ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; as if it were not enough for <hi>France</hi> to be torn in pieces by its own Hands, but it muſt alſo bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thoſe of the moſt Ancient and Formidable Enemy.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>England</hi> was a great Maſter-piece of Fortune, that is to ſay, he was equally an Object of her favourS and her frowns; he had for his Father a Homicide, an Atheiſt, a Perſon dethron'd, and under all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, which followed him ſo cloſe he could neither get Food nor Harbour but in places and among People where he was not known: The Son had his ſhare in all theſe Calamities, but they attended him no longer than during the Life of him who had drawn them upon his own Head. God, who, when he goes about to puniſh Crimes, hath an Eye upon the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Actors, took pity on the Houſe of <hi>England.</hi> As ſoon as this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36383:41"/>which it brought forth was cut off, Providence was particularly concern'd for <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, the Innocent Son of this ſo Criminal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſettled him in the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> when there was not the leaſt likelyhood he ſhould ever aſcend it; and this Affair, which ſeem'd altogether impoſſible by all the Intrigues of Policy, was brought to paſs almoſt in a moment, and that without either Trouble or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, or Expence or Blood.</p>
            <p>There remain'd nothing now but to recover thoſe Provinces of <hi>France</hi> which had been won from <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt:</hi> And <hi>Henry</hi> thought now to compaſs that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtriking a ſtroak, which he in vain attempted by force of Arms in the Reign of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. <hi>viz.</hi> the re-uniting thoſe Provinces to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and that by pretending to take part with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious <hi>French,</hi> ſuppoſing the Regent
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36383:42"/>finding it impoſſible to oppoſe him, and at the ſame time to defend her ſelf from thoſe that went about to degrade her, would immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notice of his Landing in <hi>France</hi> with a puiſſant Army, ſeek for an Accommodation, and offer him all that had been taken from the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> on Condition he would turn thoſe Arms againſt the Rebels which he had deſign'd for their aſſiſtance. So that he had no ſooner receiv'd the Earl of <hi>Boulogne</hi>'s Meſſage, which was meerly to ſift out of him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he inclin'd to concern himſelf in the bickerings which were beginning in <hi>France,</hi> but he rais'd a far more puiſſant Army than any of his Predeceſſors had ever led againſt any of the moſt Chriſtian Kings; moreover, under pretence of Obliging the Male-contents the more, he undertook to Command the Army in Perſon, and to be at all the Charges of Levying and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſporting
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36383:42"/>ſporting it; but the real truth is, his going in Perſon was rather to hinder them from Treating with him by Writing, chooſing rather by his Perſonal preſence to have an Ear open to ſuch Propoſitions as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd the Regent would ſoon make to him. Behold here the whole Foundation of the League concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under the Minority of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> never was there any one ſo Potent, or ſo cunningly driven on ſince the eſtabliſhment of the <hi>French</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; nor can the Abilities of Queen <hi>Blanch</hi> be any way better underſtood or expreſs'd, than by the recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Intrigues by which ſhe wound her ſelf out of the moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Exigences that ever Heroick Vertue was reduc'd to, and made a ſhift to preſerve the Crown in all its luſtre for the King her Son.</p>
            <p>The Male-contents had carried their Affairs with ſo much precaution and Secrecy, that the Court had not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36383:43"/>the leaſt Intelligence of them, and all the ſuſpicion the Regent had, was only grounded upon two actions, ſubject enough to a dubious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; the one was the great care which the Earl of <hi>Bologne</hi> took to Fortifie <hi>Calais,</hi> the Town of his Apennage, and the uſual place of Landing for the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> The other was the re-inforcement of the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which the Duke of <hi>Bretaign</hi> had put, at the requeſt of the late King, into the Caſtles of St. <hi>James, Beuron,</hi> and <hi>Beleſm.</hi> As there was juſt reaſon to apprehend that theſe two Innovations happened not but upon ſome Myſterious account, the Regent took an occaſion hereupon immediately to bethink her ſelf of her own ſafety; and not knowing as yet either the number or the quality of thoſe that had combin'd for her Deſtruction, all that her Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence could ſuggeſt to her, was to give Order to thoſe Military Officers
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36383:43"/>who had moſt eminently teſtified their Fidelity to her Husband, to raiſe what poſſible Force they could. 'Tis hard to reſolve, whether it were by Choice or good hap, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſucceeded according to her wiſh, but this is certain, that they acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves like Men of Honour in the Commiſſions ſhe gave them, and brought their Troops timely enough into the Field to ſave the State, by preventing the Earl of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne</hi> from ſeizing upon his Nephew the Young King, and by an Action ſo ſeaſonable, even to finiſh the War as ſoon as it was begun.</p>
            <p>The Earl thus fruſtrated of his firſt Deſign, fore-ſaw that it would not be ſo eaſie a matter as he firſt fancy'd to himſelf to Degrade his Siſter-in-Law, wherefore the better to make ſure of his Accomplices, he endeavour'd by all means poſſible to make them irreconcileable with the Regent. He knew where the greateſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36383:44"/>part of the Kings Treaſure was kept, and there it was that he made his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Effort, accordingly he ſeiz'd on it, and diſtributed it to thoſe of his Party, with this Condition, that thoſe who were neareſt to him ſhould have the greateſt ſhare. This done, he led them towards <hi>Calais,</hi> there to joyn the King of <hi>England,</hi> who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the meaſures he had taken from the Male-contents, was to make his Deſcent at that very time. But there is nothing ſo uncertain as the managing of great Enterprizes, by reaſon of that general concourſe of different Cauſes whereupon they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend for ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>The Regent loſt neither her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage nor her Judgment at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture when on the one ſide ſhe had little or nothing to hope for; and on the other, very much to fear. Never was there known to come out of her Mouth either Complaint or Reproach. She knew exactly the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36383:44"/>bad condition of her Affairs, and uſed all the Art of Diſſimulation ſhe was capable of to conceal what ſhe thought, for fear of diſcouraging thoſe faithful Perſons ſhe had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about her. She gueſs'd at the Earl of <hi>Bologne</hi>'s Deſign from the very moment he took his March, and wiſely gain'd her Advantage by the needleſs ſtop he made in <hi>Eureux,</hi> for the hindring of his paſſage. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, as ſhe concluded that <hi>France</hi> was in all likelyhood inevitably loſt if the Male-contents ſhould joyn the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſhe had recourſe to an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice which I cannot but ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh'd that no Hiſtorians ever yet made mention of. There was in <hi>England</hi> a Perſon named <hi>Hubert de Bourg,</hi> ſo conſiderable in all reſpects, that he was equall'd by no Man, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Favour or Merit; he had a Wit beyond the Common rate, and his ſhape was ſuch as what Poets uſe to attribute to <hi>Heroes.</hi> He was at
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36383:45"/>once both the moſt accompliſh'd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier and the moſt expert Captain of his Nation; and never was there <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man a truer Lover, and more Zealous Patriot of his Countrey: He ſerved both King and Kingdom to that degree, that both had an equal ſhare of Obligation to him. It was by him that the Crown had been preſerv'd in the Family of the <hi>Plantagenets,</hi> and that <hi>England</hi> had not been made a Province to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> He defended to the utmoſt <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Guien</hi> againſt <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and had ſucceſſively in the chief places of both theſe Provinces held out long Sieges, and by his obſtinate Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ruined whole Armies, never yielding to come to Capitulation till ſuch time as the very Horſes were all eaten up. Even the <hi>French</hi> his Enemies both admiring and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him for his Valour, thought they could never enough commend him
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36383:45"/>when they ſaw him here in <hi>England;</hi> and how juſt their Commendations were, he ceas'd not afterwards to give them freſh demonſtrations, ſince he alone it was who ſnatch'd out of Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> his hands the Conqueſt of this Iſland. He it was who by his Gallantry recovered the Town of <hi>Dover,</hi> and Defended it with that perſeverance, that all the <hi>French</hi> Forces ſent againſt it, were not able to re-take it. He afterwards beat them twice, once at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time before <hi>Bedford.</hi> In fine, he it was, who having diſpos'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to acknowledge him, ſet King <hi>Henry</hi> upon his Throne.</p>
            <p>And as the Obligation of this King <hi>Henry</hi> was very great, ſo His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties care and ſtudy to recompenſe him was no leſs; he confer'd upon him all the Principal Offices in the State, except that of High Admiral, for he was Grand Marſhal, Lord High Treaſurer, and Chief Juſticiary all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36383:46"/>at one time. He bad the Charge of the Tranſportation of thoſe Troops which were deſign'd for <hi>France,</hi> which Truſt while he was diſcharging with his ordinary care and vigilance, he received at that very juncture a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of 5000 Marks of Silver with a Letter which neatly and wittily ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied upon his Vanity, by inſinuating to him, that to make himſelf the moſt Illuſtrious Perſon that ever <hi>England</hi> bore, he who had lately ſettled the Crown of <hi>England</hi> upon the Head of Young King <hi>Henry</hi> his Maſter, maugre all the Force of <hi>France,</hi> ought now to make it his next bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to ſet the Crown alſo upon the Head of the Young King of <hi>France,</hi> againſt all the united Forces both of his own Subjects, and of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The weakneſs of Humane Nature never diſcovers it ſelf more plainly than when in a moment it yields to leſſer Temptations, when at other times it hath for a long while with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36383:46"/>greater. This was the Caſe of <hi>Du Bourg,</hi> who after he had been inflexible to the vaſt Offers of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf at laſt to be overcome with a petty Preſent and a poor fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous bait of Vain glory offered him by a Foreign Princeſs. He Equipp'd forth but half the number of Ships neceſſary for the Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army; and when the Noblemen, who had almoſt all in general provided to attend the King perſonally in this Expedition, came to <hi>Dover</hi> to ſee their Goods diſpos'd of on board the Ships, there was not room nor Convenience found for them; nor could it be doubted but that either the Knavery or Negligence of <hi>Du Bourg</hi> was the cauſe, whereupon immediately Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was carried to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Du Bourg</hi> was ſent for to give an account to His Majeſty, but when he came, he made ſo lame a Defence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36383:47"/>for himſelf, that the King incens'd againſt him, called him Old Traytor, and drawing his Sword, had certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly run him through the Body, had not the Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> an intimate Friend of <hi>Du Bourg,</hi> put by the thruſt, and given Opportunity to other Perſons intereſted in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of this Favourite, to interpoſe in his behalf, and to avert His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties diſpleaſure for the preſent. In the next place, they made him keep out of the way, till ſuch time as they had made his Peace, which was not long; for the King, however touch'd in the moſt ſenſible and incurable part, namely, that of Ambition, yet in the end ſuffer'd himſelf to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that the old Obligations he had to this his Favourite ought to weigh with him more than the injury lately committed. He gave him his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don freely, and in ſome time receiv'd him into his wonted Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36383:47"/>
            <p>The Regent encourag'd with the ſucceſs of her firſt Project, namely, her obſtructing with ſo much eaſe the paſſage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army over into <hi>France,</hi> put in execution a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Deſign, as no leſs bold and difficult in appearance, ſo alſo no leſs advantageous in caſe it ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: She was not ignorant how ſtrong and fervent a Paſſion ſhe had raiſed in the Heart of the Earl of <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign,</hi> and had a ſhrewd conjecture that the deſpight of ſeeing himſelf treated with ſo much indifference was the onely cauſe which induc'd him to engage with the Male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and accept of the Supreme Command of their Army. She had moreover too good an Opinion of her Charms, not to believe ſhe could at any time when ſhe pleaſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excite the Earls Love, and by never ſo ſmall an expreſſion of her Favour, call him back to his Devoir. It was now a fit time to make proof hereof,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36383:48"/>and the Regent reſolv'd to put it in agitation her own way, that is to ſay, with an Air wherein to appear Obliging, ſhe would nevertheleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit nothing of her wonted reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>The Meſſage ſhe ſent to this doubly Revolted Lover was onely this in ſhort, <hi>viz. That ſhe ſhould not be ſorry to ſee him.</hi> And this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, though the ſhorteſt and ſlendereſt certainly that ever was in this kind, produc'd an effect the ſtrangeſt that ever was heard of in the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtory in matter of Love. It ſuffic'd to tie the Earl more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than ever, to the Chains of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and her Intereſts, and to make him forget in an inſtant all the Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhe had ever ſhew'd toward him; he loſt that acuteneſs of Wit which was ſo Natural to him, and conſpir'd with the Regent to deceive himſelf. He fancied that all of a ſudden ſhe began to have a tenderneſs, though
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36383:48"/>there were all appearances imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the contrary; and this fancy of his was ſo ſtrongly rooted, that he detach'd his Troops from the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous of thoſe of the League, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of going to beat up one of the Quarters of the Kings Forces, and carried them to joyn the Army which he feign'd he was going to ſet upon.</p>
            <p>His Deſertion put the whole party of the Rebels into ſuch a diſturbance and confuſion, that all the Princes and Grandees thereof were not able to compoſe it. The moſt expedient way by which they thought to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy it, was immediately to make choice of another General, and they had the good hap to agree unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly upon a Perſon whom they judged worthy to take upon him ſo important a place; ſuch an aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hath extraordinary Merit even upon the moſt Criminal minds. They all fixt their Eyes upon <hi>Enguerrand,</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:36383:49"/>the ſecond of that Name, Lord of <hi>Couci,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Piccardy,</hi> of a Reputation too well receiv'd for any one not to ſubmit to receive Orders from him. His Valour ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted the common rate of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Actions, and the proofs he gave of it in the Wars of the Holy Land carried a greater ſemblance of Fable than of Truth, and might, though true, have better paſs'd for Romance than what we read in the moſt Romantick ſtories. He had both Conduct and Honeſty; and doubtleſs he had preſerv'd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Line, had they promoted his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with that Heireſs, inſtead of Matching her imprudently, as they did, to <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Auxerre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what reaſon he entered into the League againſt the Regent is not known, but certain it is he refuſed the Command of their Army, and that not either for want of Courage, or
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36383:49"/>deſpairing of Succeſs. All Men are not eaſily carried away to all ſorts of Crimes; and Heroick Vertue may, like the Sun, be capable of ſome ſpots that may obſcure it, but never be totally darkned, no more than this King of Stars can wholly loſe its Light. <hi>Couci</hi> moreover knew the vaſt difference between barely being of a Party in a Revolt, and being the Head or Chief of the ſaid Party; and his Honeſty became a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, if I may ſo ſay, when it ſaw it ſelf expos'd to the moſt dangerous of Civil Temptations. He never throughly fore-ſaw the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Engagment till he was juſt upon the Precipice; that is to ſay, till he found that the Charge which the Confederates would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon him was deſign'd to ſpur on his Ambition, by lifting him up to a higher pitch than ever he aſpir'd to. Beſides, he comprehended the ſenſe of thoſe Myſterious words, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36383:50"/>the quality of Parricide which lay lurking underneath, ſtartled him; he was afraid of loſing, in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced Age, that Glory which he had acquir'd in his Youth; and was unwilling to ſurvive himſelf, by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering thoſe Lawrels to fade in <hi>France</hi> which he had gain'd in <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> He teſtified ſo great an averſion for the Generalſhip, that they durſt not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it to him a ſecond time: And ſince the Memoirs which are extant of this great Perſonage make no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention of him, it is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd he quitted the League, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately retir'd to his Caſtle of <hi>Couci,</hi> there to ſpend the remnant of his days in a more innocent and quiet courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>His refuſal augmented among the Rebels that Diſorder which his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance would have compos'd, and in fine, ſhatter'd them all to pieces. The Earl of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> who had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to take the Field, kept his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:36383:50"/>in their Quarters in the Town which bears that name, and the Earl of <hi>Provence</hi> forbore to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf till ſuch time as he ſaw what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy could be apply'd to the making up of theſe Breaches. His keeping off was no leſs happy than prudent; for as much as the Earl of <hi>Bologne</hi> being now convinc'd that theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns formed againſt his Soveraign, could never ſucceed in the end, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo untoward a beginning, was the firſt who quitted that Work whereof he himſelf had laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and made an Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion apart with the Regent: What the Conditions were, is not known, but ſure enough they were not very Advantageous, ſince on the one ſide his Apennage was not at all aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and on the other ſide, the Regent had no Money to give him. A little after, the Earl of <hi>Dreux</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his Duty, obtaining onely the confirmation of the partage made
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36383:51"/>with his Brother the Duke of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The falling off of ſo many Perſons of the firſt Rank, one would think, had been enough to have broken the League, nevertheleſs there were Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Gentlemen enough ſtill left to continue it, and the Regent knew well enough that there would be a Party of the Rebels ſtill on foot, ſo long as there might with eaſe be ſound a way to remove all pretext which ſhould hinder them of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat in <hi>Bretaign</hi> and the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> in caſe they ſhould chance to be beaten in a Battel. It was a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult matcer to remove all at once two ſuch grand Refuges; and the Regent, after ſhe had along time exerciſed the utmoſt of her Wit and Cunning, effected as yet but half of what ſhe pretended to. The Duke of <hi>Bretaign</hi> remain'd ſtill inflexible, and Threats wrought now no more upon him than Promiſes had done
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36383:51"/>before, ſo that the Regent as much exaſperated as wearied out with the Obſtinacy of this Prince, turn'd more efficaciouſly her Policy another way.</p>
            <p>It was now about a dozen Years, that the Earls of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martin</hi> had lyen languiſhing in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and as theſe two Perſons were very near both Criminal alike, it ſeemed but juſt that there ſhould be as little difference put in the Favour which was to be ſhewn them as there had been in their Guilt, and was in their Puniſhment. But their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were not equal; the Earl of <hi>Dampmartin</hi> was of a Humour ſo ill contriv'd, that it was not poſſible to have any kind of Indulgence for him which he would not be apt to abuſe. The League wanted a Head, and that very thing was ſufficient to obſtruct his Deliverance; for had he been let out, he had certainly gone immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately and joyn'd the Rebels. The Earl of <hi>Flanders</hi> had more of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:36383:52"/>in him, and was not irregular in matters of Generoſity, except in ſuch Rencounters where he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd it not ſufficiently from thoſe Vices which are deſign'd to paſs for it; he had in his Soul a fund of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which facilitated his return to his Allegiance, however he had been carried away by Paſſion or Weakneſs. The Regent being inform'd of the ſtrong part and the weak of this <hi>Portuguez</hi> Prince, reſolv'd to give him that Liberty which ſhe deny'd the Earl of <hi>Dampmartin;</hi> and as ſhe never attracted ſo much Admiration as in matters of loud importance, ſo ſhe particularly accompanied this with ſo many Obliging Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the Earl of <hi>Flanders,</hi> that he not onely remained firm himſelf to the Intereſts of his Benefactreſs, but alſo accepted of the Leave given him to return to his Wife, meerly upon this very account, that he might take her wholly off, as he did, from the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36383:52"/>League, and oblige her to call home thoſe Troops which ſhe had ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Rebels Camp.</p>
            <p>The Entreagues of Court were ſucceeded by the formalities of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; the Regent after ſhe had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointed the League, ſummon'd the principal members to meet in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Chinon,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Tours.</hi> The Members ſummon'd appear'd neither at the firſt, nor ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Citation, but when they were commanded to appear the third time at <hi>Vendome,</hi> and had but twenty days time allow'd them for their appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; they conſulted among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what they had beſt to do: The moſt furious of them were of opinion, that they might leave the matter to be judg'd by <hi>Forecluſion,</hi> and only bring it to a review when the war ſhould be ended; but the wiſer ſort were of a contrary judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, alledging that it was always a troubleſome thing to be caſt in Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36383:53"/>of what nature ſoever, and that an Arreſt could not poſſibly come out againſt them without leaving a blot upon their memory; Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they concluded, that it would be neceſſary to appear by Proxy, and if the Reaſons they brought for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Cauſe, were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to satisfie her, they would at leaſt ſerve to convince the People, that they were not ſo culpable as the Regent gave out; but neither the one, nor the other of theſe Councils were follow'd, and the reſolution they took was like the way of all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Aſſemblies in this, that they choſe the very worſt of all Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents propos'd. It was carryed by the plurality of voices, that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and moſt eminent Lords of the League, ſhould repair to <hi>Vendome,</hi> with a very ſmall Train, to perſwade the Regent that they had a ſincere deſire of a reconciliation with her, preſuming, that the Regent deluded
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36383:53"/>by this fair pretence, would not fail to bring along with her, or at leaſt ſend, the King her Son, to <hi>Vendome,</hi> with a ſmall guard, by reaſon that on the one ſide, the preſence of this young Monarch would be abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary, on the other ſide, ſhe would be cautious of giving the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſuſpicion to a People, who teſtified with ſo much frankneſs their readineſs to ſubmit to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, which would be obvious, in caſe they ſhould ſee him attended with a greater number than was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al upon ſuch like Ceremonies; that the Confederates who were Maſters of <hi>Eſtampes</hi> and <hi>Corbeil,</hi> might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being percei'd draw out of thoſe two places, as many Forces as would be ſufficient to carry off the King; and that the Regent having loſt him, by whom ſhe held her Authority, would be conſtrain'd to ſeek for an agreement with thoſe whom ſhe ſeem'd before ſo much to ſlight.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:36383:54"/>
            <p>Who the Author was, of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Council, is not certainly known; ſome Hiſtorians ſay it was the Duke of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> others, the Earl of <hi>March;</hi> but from whoſe brain ſoever it proceeded, it was ſo exactly adjuſted to the Conjuncture of Affairs at that time, that nothing but Divine Providence which took particular care of the preſervation of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> could have fruſtrated the deſign. The moſt ſagacious wiſdom of this world hath its Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, and ſometimes commits ſuch failings as folly it ſelf could not be guilty of greater. Seldom are long adminiſtrations without ſome error, as if the government of States were a kind of Sea, where at one time or other there muſt needs be Shipwrack. The Regent had hitherto follow'd the Maxims of moſt exquiſite pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and her Enemies, who felt the ſharp Effects thereof, admir'd her no leſs than her friends, who had the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36383:54"/>advantage of it, but all was ſpoil'd at one daſh; For whether it were that ſhe hop'd ſuddenly to conclude a Peace, or, that ſhe rely'd too much upon the judgments of her blind Counſellors; ſhe ſent the King her Son to <hi>Vendome</hi> with a very weak guard.</p>
            <p>Never were there civil wars in <hi>France,</hi> but had this inconvenience attending, namely, that the deſigns of one party, though never ſo ſecretly carry'd, were in a moment known to the other; The Earl of <hi>Champaign</hi> had excellent Spies in the Army of the League, and never fail'd of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inform'd from time to time of whatever deſigns were form'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, in regard the chief of thoſe who were moſt privy thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, held correſpondence with him, conſequently, he had immediately notice of all the particularities of the deſign laid for ſeiſing the ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King. He advertis'd
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36383:55"/>hereof the Regent who was then at <hi>Paris;</hi> for there the Council of State detain'd her, as ſuppoſing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this Princeſs would diſcover the correſpondences of the Rebels in that great Town.</p>
            <p>The Regent was not ſo much troubled, though heartily angry at her ſelf, for her indiſcretion, at the error ſhe had committed, as in pain, till ſhe had found out a way to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it, nor was it long e're her admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inventive wit prompted her to a way which anſwer'd her deſires. She wrote to the King, who was in the <hi>Bourg de Chaſtres,</hi> to ſecure himſelf in the Caſtle of <hi>Montleher,</hi> till ſuch time as ſhe could ſend Forces ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to deliver him, and in regard the Army Royal was at too great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſhe had recourſe to the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen aſſembled all the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels, and other Officers from their reſpective Quarters, and in a moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36383:55"/>thetick Speech repreſented to them the greatneſs of the danger the King was in, and the more effectually to move her audience, ſhe gave frequent interruptions to her Speech with tears and ſobs: and after ſhe had thus mollified their hearts, ſhe prick'd them on with the thoughts of what immortal glory would attend them in being the Inſtruments of their Monarchs Preſervation: Moreover, ſhe gave them to underſtand how little hazard they would run, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they made haſte, ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels who deſign'd to ſeize upon the King, at the paſſage of <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> would fall into their mouths without going farther, the Colonels then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving aſſur'd her that they would preſently go, and get their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies together, and haſten their March, ſhe provided experienc'd under-Officers, to order and conduct them. The <hi>Parisians</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleher</hi> ſooner, and with greater
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36383:56"/>force then could have been imagin'd; and having drawn up in a large Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion, they ſet the King in the midſt of them, and brought him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them to their Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Rebels had determin'd what meaſures were to be taken to oppoſe them: But by the ſame way that the Earl of <hi>Champaign</hi> came to know their deſign, they came to know that it was he who diſcover'd it to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. However, the extraordinary deſire which they had to be reveng'd of him, did not yet ſo far blind them, but that they foreſaw it would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably more advantageous for them to make uſe of the natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of this Prince, and to draw him once more over to their Party, than unſeaſonably to endeavour his preſent miſchief. The Duke of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taign,</hi> who had no Children but one Daughter, whoſe beauty was charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough to raiſe the drooping Spirits of an ill treated Lover, had
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36383:56"/>ſhe not been endow'd beſides with a Province of large Extent, offer'd the Earl of <hi>Champaign,</hi> provided he would take part with the League, to put into his poſſeſſion the Princeſs of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and to permit him either to eſpouſe her himſelf, or to bequeath her to ſome other Prince of his houſe. This offer as advantageous as it was, the Earl refus'd, whether it were that he was not yet perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Regent conſider'd him no otherwiſe then as a property to be made uſe of, or, as hoping the two laſt Services he had render'd her, would produce at length the Effect which he had in vain expected, by all his former aſſiduities once more; he made his Love tryumph over his Ambition, and all the fruit he drew from theſe Temptations, was to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe the Regent thereof, to the end ſhe ſhould be ſenſible, that if he yielded not, ſhe was the ſole cauſe The Rebels more offended at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:36383:57"/>than they had been at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertion, conceiv'd ſo implacable a malice againſt him, that they left the Regent to her quiet and repoſe, and reſolv'd to turn their Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Champaign;</hi> they conſpire his ruine by a particular Treaty, and as they foreſaw that the Regent was too much oblig'd to abandon him to people whom he had not quitted but for her; they found a pretext ſo plauſible, that ſhe durſt not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently aſſiſt him, without commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a notorious piece of Injuſtice.</p>
            <p>Divine Providence had not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abandon'd the two Nieces of the Earl of <hi>Champaign,</hi> though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded of their Right, by their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. The Eldeſt nam'd <hi>Alice,</hi> had the fortune to be married to <hi>Hugo de Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignan,</hi> the firſt of that Name, King of <hi>Cyprus;</hi> The goodneſs of <hi>Henry</hi> Father of this Princeſs, doubtleſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd her this Match, and the Lord of <hi>Joinvile,</hi> the moſt credible of all
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36383:57"/>the Hiſtorians that write of St. <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi> hath a paſſage concerning this matter, which it will not be from the purpoſe here to abbreviate: <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Earl of <hi>Champaign,</hi> the Eldeſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Predeceſſor of <hi>Thibault,</hi> was of ſo free and liberal a diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to give to all ſorts of People, eſpecially the poor, that he was thence ſirnam'd the <hi>Large,</hi> that is to ſay, large hearted, or bountiful. He had no particular Favourite, only there was one <hi>Artaud</hi> a Citizen of <hi>Troyes,</hi> who had inſinuated into his familiarity, whether it were, that there was ſome conformity in their humours, or, that the Earl had the more conſideration, for <hi>Artaud,</hi> in regard he was the richeſt of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. One day when they were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at Church, a poor Gentleman preſented his two daughters to the Earl, and beſought him to beſtow ſomething upon them to marry them off. They were handſome, and of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:36383:58"/>an Age ſo fully ripe for Marriage, that in caſe they ſtay'd much longer unprovided for, it was to be fear'd their virtue might be in danger. <hi>Artaud</hi> knew well enough that the Prince his Exchequer was much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and brought low; and as he had many times taken upon him to anſwer for the ſaid Earl, without being thought ill of for his pains, ſo upon this occaſion he ſmartly told the Gentleman, that the Earls Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality had already brought him ſo low, that he had hardly any thing left to give.</p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo ungrateful to the quality of a Prince as Poverty, and therefore nothing ſo ill to be brook'd by them as the reproach thereof; The Earl now incens'd at the too much liberty, or, to ſay bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaucineſs of <hi>Artaud,</hi> told him he lyed, and that he had yet enough to give, if it were but an <hi>Artaud;</hi> and at the inſtant of his pronouncing the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36383:58"/>word <hi>Artaud,</hi> he made ſigns to the Gentleman to ſeiſe upon the Citizen, and to demand what Ranſome for him he pleas'd. The Gentleman ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly took hold of him, carryed him away to Priſon, and there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd him till he had paid 500 Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres, which ſerv'd for Portions for the two Damſels.</p>
            <p>The Rebels took hold of Count <hi>Henry</hi>'s Liberality, to concern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in his behalf to their own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, maintaining, that it was a thing not to be endur'd, to ſee the Eldeſt Daughter of him who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd ſo many poor People kept out from her hereditary Eſtate; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly offer'd their aſſiſtance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her reeſtabliſhment. The Queen of <hi>Cyprus</hi> took them at their word, and the <hi>Champaigneſes</hi> ſeing them enter their Countrie with two Armies, one commanded by the Duke of <hi>Bourgogne,</hi> the other by <hi>Hugo de Luſignan,</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:36383:59"/>let open the gates of all their Towns, before Earl <hi>Thibault</hi> could bring up the Army Royal to their ſuccour. The Rebels ſucceſs gave them oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to take new meaſures, they abandon'd all the pretence they had formerly made uſe of againſt the Regent, and declar'd themſelves her Majeſties moſt humble Servants, they proteſted they had taken Arms on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſtore the Queen of <hi>Cyprus</hi> to that Eſtate ſhe layd claim to, they offer'd to lay down their Arms, as ſoon as their moſt Chriſtian Majeſties ſhould have beheld with ſatisfaction and approbation the reeſtabliſhment of this Princeſs, and to decide the difference between her and her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, by a fair combate, preſuming, there were no leſs than 300 Knights, as well on the one ſide, as the other. Their Majeſties accepted the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Rebels with this reſerve, that they were to have the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign deciſion of the affair in hand,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36383:59"/>after they had try'd all ways which their prudence ſhould ſuggeſt to them, to bring the Parties to agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that above all things it was expected his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty ſhould be inveſted with the Right of Sequeſtration, that is, ſhould have the Title of all the Eſtates in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie depoſited in his Royal hands.</p>
            <p>The Rebels who found that this Expedient would not turn to any account to them, rejected it, and the Regent ſent Forces enough into <hi>Champaign,</hi> to diſlodge the Earls Enemies. She foreſaw in the end, that in pronouncing a definitive Sentence upon ſo nice a Proceſs, her Authority and Reputation would be much expos'd and brought into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; for that if her Sentence were favourable to the Earl of <hi>Champaign,</hi> all the <hi>French</hi> would be ready to tax he of notorious Injuſtice, eſpecially if ſhe ſhould make it her buſineſs in this affair, to ſerve her pretended Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36383:60"/>all the Satyrical wits would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to let fly at her, with more fury than before: on the other ſide, if ſhe ſhould decree the Queens reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in her Eſtate, of the houſe of <hi>Champaign,</hi> ſhe would be liable to be cenſur'd of Ingratitude toward Count <hi>Thibault,</hi> to whom ſhe ow'd her Regency at leaſt, if not her Life. In ſhort, which way ſoever ſhe gave her Sentence, all outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances conduce to this perſwaſion, that the Arreſt would be ſubject to a review, becauſe otherwiſe the Duke of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and the reſt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted Peers, would not have been aſſiſtant in it; ſo that the buſineſs could not but go well on the fair one's ſide: and this the Regent brought the better about by a trick, which in brief was as followeth. She repreſented to the Queen of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> that the Rebels ſending for her, was but to make her endure a long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of affliction, after a ſhort
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:36383:60"/>flaſh of joy, for that no ſooner ſhould ſhe be put into the poſſeſſion of her Fathers Eſtate by their means, but ſhe would be driven out again, and that ſhe plainly foreſaw the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels would not be in a capacity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring her the ſecond time; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince her engaging with them would ſignifie ſo little to her, there remain'd but one Expedient by which if ſhe would take her advice, ſhe might come off with honour. That ſhe had but one Son, who in regard he was oblig'd to reſide in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> would not be able to preſerve the Inheritance of <hi>Champaign</hi> any long time, though ſhe her ſelf ſhould leave the peaceable poſſeſſion of it to him: that her daughters would never find Matches in <hi>Cyprus</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their quality, that therefore it would be much better for her by yielding to an accomodation with Count <hi>Thibault,</hi> to receive a preſent ſumm of mony, and ſuch a portion
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:36383:61"/>of Land in <hi>France,</hi> as would put her into a capacity of matching her daughters into Sovereign houſes, than by ſtanding out to be reduc'd to a Condition of having nothing to give them.</p>
            <p>The Queen of <hi>Cyprus</hi> was not without thoſe failings which are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with perſons of little or no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the World; ſhe deſpair'd of ever bringing to paſs thoſe affairs, in which ſhe was bauk'd at firſt, and had too much impatience in the midſt of ill fortune, to wait the turning of the Tide. She had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd a belief that it was not the will of God ſhe ſhould ever be Counteſs of <hi>Champaign,</hi> becauſe ſhe had twice in vain made her pretenſions to it, and in the heat of this perſwaſion, ſhe conſented to a Treaty, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the affair to any of thoſe that had been the occaſion of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her over into <hi>France:</hi> She was contented to accept of 40000 Livres
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:36383:61"/>of ready mony, and the Counties of <hi>Brienne</hi> and <hi>Joigni,</hi> for all ſhe pretended to of her Fathers and Mothers Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Earl <hi>Thibault</hi> was not ſo indiſcreet to refuſe an agreement which was of ſuch advantage to him, but he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed money, and the ſumm he was to raiſe was ſo conſiderable, that his Subjects harraſs'd by the quartering of ſo great Forces as had lately been among them, were not able to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him, and no leſs unable to aſſiſt him, were the reſt of the Feudata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries his friends; ſo that if it were any where to be had, it muſt be had out of the Kings Exchequer; but the Regent was too prudent to take any thing out from thence, but upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Terms, and what ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations ſhe and the King, her Son, had to the Earl, when all things came to be weigh'd in the ballance of Truth, it would eaſily appear that he had done them as much harm as
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:36383:62"/>good, having poiſon'd the Father of the one, and the Husband of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. His power too great for any Vaſſal, gave him the boldneſs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this crime, and the only way to be reveng'd on him for it, was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to ſuch a Condition, that his Succeſſours ſhould never dare to have any thoughts of the like at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, as not being able to execute them with Impunity. In ſhort, the deſign in hand was to weaken the houſe of <hi>Champaign,</hi> and this preſent occaſion was too favourable to be neglected. The Regent waited the time when this Summ ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd of her, and when the buſineſs was mov'd, ſhe made anſwer ſhe was ready to lend, provided ſuch Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were given for the repayment thereof, as was fit to be accepted by a King's Mother, and Governeſs. The Earl offer'd her Majeſty to engage thoſe Counties he poſſeſs'd in the heart of the Kingdom; but it was
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:36383:62"/>anſwer'd him, that this kind of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement would be ſubject to grand Inconveniences and hazards, both as to the repaiment of Principal and Intereſt; and the care which was to be had to repair waſtes, and make Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements; that it became a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs to avoid as much as poſſibly ſhe could, all kind of Embaraſments in the affairs of her Pupil: In fine, if the Earl had a mind to ſell, ſhe was willing rather to purchaſe than to lend mony. The Earl ſaw well enough that they went about to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine him, in ſo ſubtile a manner, as that he ſhould have no certain foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation or pretence of complaint; he was a man of too much ſenſe and ſpirit, not to be troubled to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus dealt with, and to find by theſe proceedings, that the Regent was far from ever having any incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for him: but it was no time now to declare his reſentment, and he foreſaw that in caſe he refus'd to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36383:63"/>relinquiſh a part of his Inheritance, he ſhould be ſure to loſe all; Upon which he conſented to ſell the King, his Earldoms of <hi>Charters, Blois,</hi> and <hi>Sancerre,</hi> and the Viſcountſhip of <hi>Chateaudun;</hi> and out of the money of this ſale, Her Majeſty deducted 40000 Livres which ſhe paid immediately to the Queen of <hi>Cyprus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rebels by this Tranſaction being fruſtrated of the pretence, they had of treating the Earl as an Enemy, and on the other ſide, not being able eaſily to reſolve upon forgiving him, found out another Expedient, which was no leſs advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to their Party. They laid Treaſon to his Charge, impeaching him of the untimely death of his late Sovereign Lord King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. by poyſon given him, and offer'd to undergo the ſevereſt penalties that could be inflicted upon falſe accuſers, if they did not plainly prove him guilty of two Crimes, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36383:63"/>him unfit for humane Society, that is to ſay, of high Treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Sovereign Lord, and of being a Traitor againſt his Country. This they urg'd with Arms in their hands, and the danger which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Crown, from their impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heat, was thought ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that all the grand Miniſters of the Kings Council were of Opinion, that the beſt way would be to give, them ſome ſatisfaction. The Count himſelf was of the ſame Sentiment for quietneſs ſake, and it was with his own conſent, that the Queen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Treaty with them, made the chief Condition of their laying down their Arms, to be the Earl of <hi>Champaign</hi>'s taking upon him the <hi>Croiſada,</hi> and ſetting out immediately for the holy Land, attended with a hundred Knights at leaſt, to be maintain'd at his own Charge.</p>
            <p>This was a very notable Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in regard it equally pleas'd both
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36383:64"/>Parties; For on the one ſide, the Earl found it very advantageous to him, in regard, both his Crime met with a far gentler puniſhment than it really deſerv'd, or he could have hop'd for, had he been brought to Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and his Reputation was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſalv'd, by going in a croud of ſo many innocent perſons, as daily went upon this Expedition, upon no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motive than their moſt ardent zeal. On the other ſide, the Rebels al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo obtain'd what they deſir'd; for, beſides that they had a long time of deliverance from their Enemy, and the ſatisfaction of having put him upon an Expedition, from whence few valiant men live to return; If the accuſation wherewith they branded him were not made out in full, it was at leaſt in part, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, there were among the <hi>Croi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſado'd</hi> Champions many innocent perſons, there were alſo many cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable; and as divers Princes and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36383:64"/>Great men led Armies over into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine,</hi> merely for the accompliſhing of thoſe religious vows they had made for the recovery of the holy places, where Jeſus Chriſt had been converſant, and died for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind; So there were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of no leſs grandure, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook this Voyage, or rather Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, as a penance enjoyn'd, and to obtain abſolution of thoſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Cenſures, which they lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And this was the caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>England,</hi> who, for his Aſſaſſination of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> had this penitential Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age enjoyn'd him by Pope <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the third, which our Earl of <hi>Champaign</hi> ſo willingly accepts.</p>
            <p>Civil wars and the Defluctions of the body end much after the ſame manner, that is to ſay, by diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves all at once upon the weakeſt part, and throwing on it a greater weight than it is able to bear.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36383:65"/>The <hi>French</hi> were almoſt brought to a right underſtanding, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would not eaſily conſent to lay down their Arms; they earneſtly preſs'd to be employ'd in proſecuting the deſign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th. and there was reaſon to fear, leſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of their demand might occaſion new troubles. Never was there a fairer proſpect of the Conqueſt of <hi>Languedoc;</hi> the longer the delay, the greater would be the difficulty, and the Intereſts of State were not to be neglected, ſo long as they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by thoſe of Religion. In order hereunto, the Regent reſolv'd to drive the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> to the utmoſt extremity; and the better to aſſure her ſelf of the greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage poſſible in all humane appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſhe made it her firſt buſineſs to deprive this Prince, whoſe ruine ſhe deſign'd, of the ſureſt refuge he had to truſt to.</p>
            <p>It hath been already obſerv'd that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36383:65"/>the Earl of <hi>Provence</hi> was his Couſin, and a Prince in like manner as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, of the houſe of <hi>Catalogue. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc</hi> had expectation of aſſiſtance more ways than one. Thoſe of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> were in a Condition to aid them, if not directly, yet at leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, being at that time the moſt free from war of any people in <hi>France,</hi> and their Prince the moſt mony'd man of any Prince in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> Mony was the main thing the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> wanted, and but for the want of which he could not have wanted Souldiers, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Excommunications thunder'd againſt him from the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> Above all things therefore the Earl of <hi>Provence</hi> muſt of neceſſity be taken off; him the Regent knew to be a ſincere man and a moſt punctual obſerver of his word; wherefore ſhe repreſented to him, by ſecret Meſſengers, that he was now grown old, and could not, if
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36383:66"/>he regarded his health, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd his true Intereſt, engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> his quarrel, without drawing an inevitable war upon <hi>Provence,</hi> let him uſe all the faution he could. That he had only our daughters, and the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> but one, ſo that ſince the houſe of <hi>Catalonia</hi> was drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a period, he could not better conſult for the honour and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Family, than by making an Alliance with that of <hi>France,</hi> which beyond all diſpute, was the nobleſt in the world. That the Eldeſt of the <hi>Provencian</hi> Princeſſes could not be more happily matcht than with the young King of <hi>France;</hi> that this propoſal was not ſo much upon the account of her Eſtate, as of her matchleſs beauty, and the charming ſweetneſs of her Nature; and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to the Earl that this Alliance was not in the leaſt promoted, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the uniting of his Eſtate
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36383:66"/>to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> there ſhould be a renunciation made to any ſuch pretenſion upon the contract of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the King, with his Eldeſt daughter, and free leave given him to divide all he had among his three younger daughters, or to give it to her of the three, whom he preferr'd before the reſt. The Earl of <hi>Provence</hi> could never have been more eaſily tempted than by two ſuch ſoft and obliging Proportions, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding his Life in Tranquility, and repoſe, and the liberty to diſpoſe his Eſtate as he pleas'd; For beſides that, he was much of the temper of thoſe effeminate Princes, who hate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than buſineſs: he was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken with the vice of thoſe who happen to have Children in their old Age, that is to ſay, he lov'd the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Beatrice</hi> his youngeſt daughter better than any of the other three, to her he deſign'd to leave <hi>Provence,</hi> and as a man is apt for the moſt part
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:36383:67"/>to give way to the belief of what he earneſtly and conſtantly deſires, he perſwaded himſelf that in preferring the youngeſt, he ſhould do no wrong to the three Elder daughters, ſince it was his intention to leave them his Treaſures which he look'd upon as treble the value of his Sovereignty.</p>
            <p>He fancy'd, if the King of <hi>France</hi> by marrying of his Eldeſt daughter, ſhewd himſelf an approver of what he had determin'd, who ever ſhould have the two next in Marriage, would not dare to gainſay it; and he had ſo great confidence in the Regents word, that he doubted not in the leaſt of her promiſe, however, ſhe deferr'd the Nuptials for ſome years by reaſon of the minority of the young Couple. All theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations diſpos'd him ſo perfectly to a Compliance, that he beheld the ruine of the Count of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> with as much inſenſibility, as if he had been neither his Relation, nor his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36383:67"/>Neighbour. In fine, the Regent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſur'd that the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> could not receive any ſuccours from <hi>Provence,</hi> and out of fear of any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to come to them from <hi>Spain,</hi> in regard the <hi>Aragonians</hi> and <hi>Caſtilians</hi> were at wars together, ſent the <hi>French</hi> Army into <hi>Languedoc</hi> under the Command of <hi>Imbert de Beaujeu,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>France,</hi> a Captain, whom <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Montfort</hi> firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd in the war.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> did not all this while lye ſtil; but whether it were that he perceiv'd the League would not laſt long, or, whether he grew ſenſible of the error he had committed in not taking advantage of the perplexity the Regent had been envolv'd in, to recover entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what he had loſt, he made haſte to take the Field, and laid Siege to the Town of <hi>Caſtel Saraſin,</hi> the ſtrongeſt next <hi>Avignon,</hi> of all that the <hi>French</hi> held in <hi>Languedoc;</hi> he
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36383:68"/>found it well Garriſon'd, and a place of too great ſtrength, what ever he had fancy'd, for him eaſily to take, which was the principal cauſe of his utter ruine, ſince the unprofitable attempts he made to take it by Force coſt him all his beſt Souldiers: and thinking it derogatory to his honour not to take it by Storm, he loſt ſo much time in making his approaches and Batteries, that when at laſt he was driven to accept of it by Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, the beſieged were ſcarce got out before the <hi>French</hi> Army return'd into <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was no leſs powerful than that which had been there before, under the Command of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th; for beſides that, ſcarce any one of the Feudataries was wanting, the Clergy reſolving to pluck up Root and Branch, all that was remaining of Hereſie in the Kingdom, thought it not enough to ſend thoſe Souldiers which they were oblig'd to ſet out
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36383:68"/>by the Fiefs they held of the Crown; their zeal carry'd them yet farther, and the opinion they had, that it was a holy war they were engag'd in, becauſe the Popes Legate march'd with the Croſs at the Head of the Army, made them open their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wider, and they doubled thoſe Companies formerly rais'd. Nor was this their Liberality thought altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enough to expreſs their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome of the Prelates who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to endure the hardships of war, put on Arms themſelves, as <hi>Amelius</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Narbon,</hi> and <hi>Foulk</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Secul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no leſs encourag'd by this Example then by the plenary indulgence the holy See granted, flock'd from all parts to take the Field, and added by their concourſe ſo much ſtrength and power to the Army, that the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> was forc'd to quit the Field. The <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſian</hi> Towns which roſe againſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36383:69"/>the <hi>French,</hi> at the firſt report of their diviſions; ſeeing them afterwards ſo ſtrong repented of their incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and endeavour'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the univerſal deſolation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were threatned; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream rigour which was exercis'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt that ſtood out, ſtriking terrour into the reſt. The Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble no ſooner appear'd before any Town, but the Keys were immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurrender'd, even the Garriſon of Caſtle <hi>Saraſin</hi> made Propoſal to the Burghers of the Town, to come to Capitulation before Summons ſent; So that this ſtrong Town which had before endur'd a long Siege, ſent their Deputies to the <hi>French</hi> before they ſat down before their Walls. All ſubmitted but <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and this great Town whoſe Colonies had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly peopled ſo many Countries of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> was now forc'd for its defence, to admit of a foreign aid, drawn from all the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36383:69"/>parts, even thoſe moſt infected with Hereſie. In the Siege of this place, the <hi>French</hi> who were become better inſtructed than formerly, by the Experience they had gain'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Avignon,</hi> order'd their affairs with very much prudence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct: they deſign'd, 'tis true, to take <hi>Tholouſe</hi> by Storm, but it was by ſuch Methods as Military Diſcipline taught them. They gain'd ground by degrees, and manag'd their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Battery with wonderful ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; and by their inceſſant and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous playing made wider Breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the Wall than the beſieged, though conſiderable in number, were able to repair: by which means the Town was reduc'd to inevitable dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being loſt: the Towns men remembred that the Town of <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> had been given over to plunder and pillage, and that their's had no reaſon to expect more favour, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither leſſ rich, nor leſs crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:36383:70"/>Thus not coming to a clear ſenſe of their misfortune, till at a time when it was too late to avoid the danger, they fancy'd it greater than really it was, and their diſturb'd Imagination caus'd them in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to loſe that reſpect which till then they had preſerv'd for their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, as Criminal and unfortunate as he was.</p>
            <p>They form'd a Conſpiracy, ſo much the more dangerous, by how much the better it was regulated. They ſent Deputies to their Earl to advertiſe him, that if he would not that very day beſtir himſelf effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to treat in their behalf, they were reſolv'd themſelves to treat the next day without him. The Earls ſtrength in <hi>Tholouſe</hi> was at that time not very great; for though he had a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Siege brought into the Town a number of <hi>Albigenſes</hi> out of the Neighbouring parts which were moſt devoted to him, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:36383:70"/>that their Goods or Eſtates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeiz'd by the Catholicks, their chiefeſt hopes were in him for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs. It was the fate of the greateſt part of theſe Hereticks to be ſlain ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Sallies that were made for the burning of the battring En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, or in defence of the Walls; ſo that the Towns-men who in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Siege were the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Defendants, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the end the ſtrongeſt: and thus the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to take Laws from thoſe to whom he had intended to have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Laws, and deſir'd leave of the Conſtable to ſend to the Regent to aſſure her he was ready to receive what Conditions her Majeſty ſhould be pleas'd to impoſe upon him.</p>
            <p>The Conſtables Intereſt preſerv'd <hi>Tholouſe</hi> from pillage, and all manner of violence, in regard he was promis'd the Government. His power extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far, as to conclude a Ceſſation
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36383:71"/>of Arms, and he ſign'd the agreement after he had taken ſuch Sureties as were requiſite upon ſuch like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Here it is that a moſt proper opportunity offers it ſelf to ſpeak of Queen <hi>Blanche</hi>'s Grand Maſter piece, in matter of Negotiation; and the Treaty here following, is held to have been one of the beſt manag'd Treaties that ever was concluded for the advantage of <hi>France,</hi> ſince it was firſt a Monarchy; however, it cannot be here represented entire, ſince the Regent had but one part in it, the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Court of <hi>France</hi> being both equally concern'd; and the Pope's Intereſts being neither manag'd with leſſ heat, nor taking up leſs time in debate than thoſe of the King of <hi>France.</hi> The ſame Legate we have already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, had here a great opportunity of ſhewing his vaſt abilities, and the notable proficiency he had made in the knowledge of the Cabinet: here
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36383:71"/>he laid the Foundation of thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, the holy See ſoon after gain'd, and to this day poſſeſſeth in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The more particular mention of the Intrigues of this great Miniſter of State, will be beſt reſerv'd for a diſcourſe, wherein the Rights of the moſt Chriſtian King to the Town of <hi>Avignon,</hi> and the Earldom of <hi>Venaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> ſhall come to be examin'd. Here we ſhall only obſerve, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent was too prudent to aſſent to the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> his Propoſitions offer'd in Council, or, to conclude an Accomodation with him in that haſte he propos'd. She was yet ſcarce diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged from a civil war rais'd prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally againſt her Authority; and ſhe was too diſcreet to imagine, that the readieſt way to oblige the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of the Rebels to lay down their Arms, would be to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the affair of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> the greateſt affair that had been known
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:36383:72"/>in <hi>France,</hi> ſince the third Race, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the advice of the Barons of the Realm. It was therefore thought fit to invite the Barons to a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the Deputies of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> and the Town of <hi>Meaux</hi> was made choice of for the place of Aſſembly, not only as being moſt commodious for the Feudataries, whoſe Reſidences were almoſt equally diſtant from it, but alſo in reſpect of its nearneſs to <hi>Paris,</hi> by which means the place would be the more eaſily ſupplied with ſuch a quantity of Proviſions as would be neceſſary for ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and ſo great a Concourſe of People.</p>
            <p>The pleaſant Seaſon of the Year <hi>viz.</hi> 1228. made the Reſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the greater; and ſuch as for their paſt faults fear'd the Courts diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, obtain'd of the Regent all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary aſſurances both as to their coming, their ſtay, and their return; but it was no very eaſy matter to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:36383:72"/>quiet their minds as for the time to come, and the Regent her ſelf went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in vain to ſatisfie them by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means. They went, or to ſay bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ran to the War of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> with a Tranſport of Zeal, which gave them not time to make ſuch Reflections as concern'd their own proper Conduct, till after ſuch time as Hereſie was almoſt ſubdued. They had conſider'd the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> as an Enemy to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> ſo long as they had their Swords in their hands; but from that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they laid down their Arms, their Averſion ſo totally ceas'd, that paſs'd all at once, and without any <hi>Medium</hi> from the extremity of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to extremity of pity. It was no extraordinary thing to them to ſee Rebel Vaſſals ruin'd, and the Reign of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Auguſt</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſufficient Examples thereof. There was not any of thoſe whoſe Eſtates they had ſeen confiſcated, ſo culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36383:73"/>as the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Crime of high Treaſon, both as to God and man, which he had more than once committed: he was, if not the Author of a very dangerous Hereſie, yet, at leaſt, the entertainer of it from the firſt broachers, and the cheriſher of it, as I may ſo ſay, in his boſome: he thought it not enough to hinder Royal Juſtice from ſeiſing on the Perſons, and enquiring into the Crimes of thoſe who taught it in his Province; but he himſelf became a Preacher thereof, contrary to the Genius of the <hi>French</hi> Nobility, who had at that time an Antipathy both for the Doctrine, and thoſe who were engag'd in it. He alone had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted more Catholicks than all the reſt of the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete the meaſure both of his obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate pravity of Nature, and of the misfortune that attended it, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laps'd into the ſame Hereſie he had
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:36383:73"/>conſented to abjure; which alone was enough to render the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> irreconcilable to him.</p>
            <p>There was now no place left for Excuſe or Complaint, and there were ſuch Circumſtances in his Degradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as have ſcarce been known in the Caſe of any other Criminal. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd a War which had been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken chiefly for his chaſtiſement; he ſubmitted himſelf before he was driven to the laſt Extremity: he came to Terms in a Town, wherein he might have held out a longer time by much: he pretended to no hopes of Favour, but in the Clemency of their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>The Indulgences formerly us'd by the moſt Chriſtian Kings, to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>France,</hi> bred up in the ſame Principles, were now no leſs favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apply'd to the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> for never were Fiefs ſeen to change their Family; and the Relations, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Deſcendants of Criminals,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36383:74"/>had alwayes the Forfeitures of the Eſtates remitted to them, provided on the one ſide, they were never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with them in their Crimes, and on the other ſide, were capable of the Homage requir'd. All this while the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> his Fief, was by the Female ſide; for it was well known that a Woman brought it into the houſe of <hi>Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi> The ſaid Earl had only one daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who being but nine Years of Age, could not poſſibly be charg'd with the leaſt concernment in any of her Fathers Crimes. <hi>Languedoc</hi> had been poſſeſs'd by his Anceſtors for 22 Generations, and it would have been thought hard for the miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the preſent poſſeſſor to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine a Family, wherein 21 Perſons ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively have been free from all Tainture. In fine, if it were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous in one ſenſe, for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to augment her Authority, by reuniting to the Kings demeans the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36383:74"/>Eſtate of one of the moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Peers of <hi>France,</hi> it would be dangerous in another ſenſe, ſince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch an attempt as this, all the reſt of the Feudataries of the ſaid Crown, as well in general, as in particular, would be concern'd to hinder it, for fear this one Spark kindled ſhould raiſe a Flame great enough to catch hold of each of them in their turn, and give them ſuch occaſions of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, as muſt needs incite them to a Revolt; ſo that in the end the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their puniſhment, would be an inevitable occaſion of empairing that Grandure, which at preſent gave luſtre to the Crown.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> came off handſomly enough, in the declaring of what they had in their mind, and the Regent who had heard them more than once; found a way to ſatisfie them without neglecting in the main, the Intereſts of her Son. She agreed with the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> his Deputies
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:36383:75"/>upon Conditions more advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than he could have hop'd for: ſhe conſented that their Prince ſhould be reeſtabliſh'd in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> upon Condition, only the Fortifications ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh'd: ſhe permitted him the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et poſſeſſion of this large Province as long as he liv'd, and let him know withal, that ſhe deſign'd nothing leſs than to keep the Princeſs his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of her hereditary poſſeſſion: on the contrary, ſhe would take care to preſerve it entire to her Poſterity. It was her opinion the Princeſs could not be better provided for, than by being eſpous'd to <hi>Alphonſo</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> Earl of <hi>Poitou,</hi> being of the ſame Age with her, neither did ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any other Security for the Earls performance of his word, but that the Princeſs ſhould be brought up at Court. She inſiſted indeed, to have the Articles of Marriage inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Treaty of peace, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36383:75"/>handſomly took occaſion to have this one Article ſlip'd in, <hi>viz.</hi> that in Caſe both the young married Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould dye without Iſſue, <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc</hi> ſhould be again united to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> as indeed it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Her pretence for this Article was, that no perſon might receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prejudice, ſince St. <hi>Lewis</hi> was to eſpouſe the Eldeſt Daughter of the Earl of <hi>Provence,</hi> preſumptive Heireſs of the Princeſs of <hi>Tholouſe;</hi> and in Truth, ſhe in ſuch fort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed this great Affair, which gave jealouſie to all the world, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy could find any cauſe to murmur at it.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>March</hi> by this means was gain'd, and his only daughter contracted to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the King's youngeſt Brother.</p>
            <p>Thus the Earl of <hi>Bretaign</hi> was left alone in the League, whoſe obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was, that he choſe rather to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the ſole Mark of all the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:36383:76"/>
               <hi>French</hi> Forces now united together, than to accept of thoſe advantageous Conditions offer'd him by the Queen. The very Civilities ſhe ſhew'd him at a juncture of time when all things ſeem'd to conſpire his ruine, exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the ſpirit of this Capricious Perſon; and becauſe the Conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own guilt repreſented to him all kindneſſes and good Offices done him as Counterfeit, he conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently fancy'd what the Regent did to oblige him, to be but meer For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and done only to draw him into a farther ſnare; and upon this falſe preſumption, he inſtantly went and treated with <hi>England.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent was ſoon advertis'd hereof, and reſolv'd to loſe no time in driving on the buſineſs to a Head, the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter began to come on very ſharp, and the time was overpaſt for ſetting out the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet to Sea, for the relief of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> which was now brought to do Homage to the King
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36383:76"/>of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> encouraged by the preſence of their moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſties, went directly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort Siege took the Town of <hi>Angers,</hi> which King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 8th, having taken from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> had put into the hands of the <hi>Bretons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen had no ſooner diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd what ſhe went about in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou,</hi> but with the ſame Expedition and Diligence as ſhe had march'd thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe return'd and laid cloſe Siege to <hi>Beleſme,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Perch,</hi> and the ſtrongeſt place the Enemy then had. It was thought impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but the Rams and other Engines of Battery having at laſt thrown down the Walls, made it appear to be otherwiſe. The beſieged came to Capitulation, but not till ſuch time as the Beſiegers were almoſt tir'd with continual labour, for they had as hard a task to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the rigours of the Seaſon, as from the Arms of the beſieged.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:36383:77"/>the extremity of Cold cauſing ſuch a Paralytick Diſtemper among them, that thoſe affected therewith, could hardly eſcape death, the only way was, to ſit basking continually by a good fire ſide. Thus, through one, or other obſtacle, their Majeſties found it a difficult matter to march their Army into <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and this proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly was the main Reaſon, why they ſought out another Expedient for the putting an end to the War.</p>
            <p>The Regent ſent to the Nobility of <hi>Bretaign,</hi> and repreſented to them, that their Lands would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be laid waſte, if they did not immediately put themſelves under the Kings Protection, that the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhe warn'd them of, was very near at hand, and that their Duke would not be able to help them: then ſhe made her Addreſs to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>France,</hi> and requir'd to have <hi>Bretaign</hi> put into the King's hands, the Parliament yielded to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:36383:77"/>and acquitted this Province of their Homage to their Duke, who thereupon, was depriv'd of the principal Refuge he had to truſt to, and his Troops now no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ſuch Gentlemen, as held of him by any Tenure of Land, drop'd away by degrees, and were all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pierc'd in a ſhort time; He was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in fine to this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> either to keep himſelf ſhut up in ſome ſtrong Town, or, to paſs over into <hi>England:</hi> the firſt of theſe two extreams would infallibly bereave him of his Liberty, if not of Life alſo: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, by forcing him to quit his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would reduce him to a private Condition. Thoſe who by chance or accidentarrive to Sovereignty, more grievouſly reſent a fall, than thoſe whom a natural Title, and the Laws have inveſted with a power of Reigning. Thus ſtreightned and perplex'd, he reſolv'd at a Venture to ſubmit to whatever the Regent
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36383:78"/>would impoſe upon him; and in Concluſion, came off with the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendry of the Lands, which the houſe of <hi>Bretaign</hi> poſſeſs'd in <hi>France,</hi> beſides, the Dutchy; and giving in Security both for himſelf, and his Heirs, that the ſaid Dutchy ſhould from that time forward, never hold of any but the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> The firname of <hi>Mauclerk</hi> ſtuck up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to future Ages, for having ſo ill taken his meaſures with the <hi>French</hi> Rebels, and with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that in the end he was left alone to bear the whole bront of the Controverſie. And now Queen <hi>Blanch</hi> had no more to trouble, or, obſtruct the quiet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Her Regency, but through the vain Attempts of thoſe that labour'd to oppoſe Her, was ſo much the more ſtrongly fix'd and eſtabliſh'd therein.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:78"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome <hi>Novels,</hi> and <hi>Plays</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>NOVELS.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>ZElinda,</hi> a Fam'd Romance.</item>
               <item>2 Happy Slave, in three Parts.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Count Brion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Count Gabales.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Hatag;</hi> or the Amours of the King of <hi>Tamaran.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 Madam <hi>Lavalier,</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 Madam and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 Madam <hi>Colonna</hi>'s Memoires.</item>
               <item>9 Queen of <hi>Majork,</hi> two Parts.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11 <hi>Heroine Muſquetier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12 Princeſs of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 Obliging Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>14 Fatal Prudence.</item>
               <item>15 Princeſs of <hi>Fez.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16 Diſorders of Love.</item>
               <item>17 Triumph of Love.</item>
               <item>18 Victorious Lovers.</item>
               <item>19 <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Almanzaida.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>20 Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21 <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> or, the Defender of his Miſtreſs.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:36383:79"/>
               <item>22 <hi>Nicoſtratis,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23 Amorous Abbeſs.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>Homais</hi> Queen of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>25 Pilgrim, in two Parts.</item>
               <item>26 <hi>Meroveus,</hi> Prince of the Blood Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>27 Life of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>28 Extravagant Poet.</item>
               <item>29 <hi>Memoires Gallant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>30 Inſtruction for a Young Noble Man.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Tartuff,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Puritan.</item>
               <item>2 Forc'd Marriage, or the Jealous Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Engliſh Monſieur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 All miſtaken, or the Mad Couple.</item>
               <item>5 Generous Enemies, or the Ridiculous Lovers.</item>
               <item>6 The Plain-Dealer.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Sertorius,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Nero,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>9 <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Overthrow.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Gloriana,</hi> or the Court of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11 <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</item>
               <item>12 <hi>Mithridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 <hi>Oedipus</hi> King of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14 <hi>Caeſar Borgia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15 <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or the Force of Love.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:36383:79"/>
               <item>16 Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> or the Witty Falſe One.</item>
               <item>17 The Fond Husband, or the Plotting Siſters.</item>
               <item>18 Eſquire <hi>Old-Sap,</hi> or the Night-Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</item>
               <item>19 Fool turn'd Critick.</item>
               <item>20 Virtuous Wife, or Good Luck at laſt.</item>
               <item>21 The Fatal Wager.</item>
               <item>22 <hi>Andromache.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23 Country Wit.</item>
               <item>24 <hi>Caliſto,</hi> or the Chaſte Nymph.</item>
               <item>25 Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
               <item>26 Ambitious Stateſman, or the Loyal Favourite.</item>
               <item>27 Miſery of Civil War.</item>
               <item>28 The Murder of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>29 <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>30 <hi>Hamlet</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>31 The Orphan, or the Unhappy Marriage.</item>
               <item>32 The Soldiers Fortune.</item>
               <item>33 <hi>Tamerlain</hi> the Great.</item>
               <item>34 Mr. <hi>Limberham,</hi> or the Kind Keeper.</item>
               <item>35 Miſtaken Husband.</item>
               <item>36 Notes of <hi>Morocco,</hi> by the Wits.</item>
               <item>37 <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or the Unhappy Favourite.</item>
               <item>38 Virtue Betray'd, or <hi>Anna Bullen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>39 King <hi>Leir.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:36383:80"/>
               <item>40 <hi>Abdellazor,</hi> or the <hi>Moor</hi>'s Revenge.</item>
               <item>41 Town-Fop, or Sir <hi>Tim. Tawdery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>42 <hi>Rare en tout,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Comedy.</item>
               <item>43 <hi>Moor</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>44 Country Wife.</item>
               <item>45 City Politicks.</item>
               <item>46 Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>47 Rehearſal.</item>
               <item>48 King and no King.</item>
               <item>49 <hi>Philaſter,</hi> or Love lies a Bleeding.</item>
               <item>50 Maids Tragedy.</item>
               <item>51 Grateful Servant.</item>
               <item>52 Strange Diſcovery.</item>
               <item>53 Atheiſt, or the Second Part of the Soldiers Fortune.</item>
               <item>54 Wit without Money.</item>
               <item>55 Little Thief.</item>
               <item>56 Valiant <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>57 <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>58 <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>59 Amorous Prince.</item>
               <item>60 <hi>Dutch</hi> Lovers.</item>
               <item>61 Woman Rules.</item>
               <item>62 Reformation.</item>
               <item>63 <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>64 Love-Tricks.</item>
               <item>65 <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>66 Fatal Jealouſie.</item>
               <item>67 Monſieur <hi>Ragou.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36383:80"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
